<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Casimir, king o[f] Po[land] [subtitle lacking]</title>
            <title>Casimir, roy de Pologne. English</title>
            <author>Rousseau de la Valette, Michel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92018</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R2051</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42283</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36272557</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36272557</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92018)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2237:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Casimir, king o[f] Po[land] [subtitle lacking]</title>
                  <title>Casimir, roy de Pologne. English</title>
                  <author>Rousseau de la Valette, Michel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 204 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Charles Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Lond[on] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: title page torn, with loss of text; stained and tightly bound. Best copy available for photographing.</note>
                  <note>Missing text supplied from Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kazimierz --  IV Jagiellończyk, --  King of Poland, 1427-1492.</term>
               <term>Poland --  History --  Casimir IV, 1447-1492.</term>
               <term>Poland --  Court and courtiers.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Caſimer, KING THE NORABLE JOHN CROPLEY <hi>ARONET.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Printed for <hi>Charles Smith</hi> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150241:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150241:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE Sir JOHN CROPLEY <hi>BARONET.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SO many circumſtances Conſpire, and I am prompted by ſo many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations
<pb facs="tcp:150241:3"/>to make you this preſent, that I can no way decline it; without taxing my ſelf with ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. And yet after all I muſt Confeſs. I think this leſs an acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment than a juſt tribute to your merit and your Vertues. For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding you have all the advantages of Body and Mind, you are ſo far from valuing your ſelf for them, and making Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade of your accompliſhments,
<pb facs="tcp:150241:3"/>that you uſe all your en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to conceal them from the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne all thoſe vanities which Perſons of your age and Circumſtances do uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly purſue and hug with ſo much eagerneſs and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Thus Modeſty ſeems to be your Darling Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, tho you entertain and practiſe all the others on every Occaſion. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to comply with that Modeſty you ſo much cheriſh I ſhall quit this
<pb facs="tcp:150241:4"/>point, which is indeed above deſcription, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to give you, Sir, ſome account of the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I make you, which is an exact Relation of the Wars of the Crown of <hi>Poland</hi> with the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> in <hi>Caſimers</hi> Reign, who being an Amourous Prince, it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe containes an Account of his Love intrigues, which indeed occaſioned his own Ruine and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation of all, or the great
<pb facs="tcp:150241:4"/>eſt part of his Kingdom. All herein related, being generally matter of Fact, you will find but little of Fiction or Romances, and therefore cannot pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to meet with that delicate turne of Thought and of Expreſſion that might be expected in a piece that depended wholly, or principally upon fancy. Yet the Naked truth has ſuch charmes, as I hope will more than countervail for that diſadvantage. Such
<pb facs="tcp:150241:5"/>as it is, Sir, I lay it at your feet and beg it may meet with your acceptance, which I was the more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to do, and am in the more hopes of, for that of all the parts of Learning, I have found History to have ever had moſt of your kindneſs and favour; for which reaſons I apprehended you would be the more willing to grant it your Protection, and me a Pardon for this
<pb facs="tcp:150241:5"/>Preſumption, who am with all manner of Zeal and reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt Humble and moſt Obedient Servant. F. S.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:150241:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150241:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CASIMER</hi> KING of POLAND.</head>
            <p>THE Kingdom of <hi>Poland</hi> is Elective, and yet the <hi>Polan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> have that laudable Cuſtom of ever chooſing a Prince of the Family of their Kings. Thus <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> was no ſooner dead, than that Prince <hi>Caſimer</hi> his Brother was Elected in his place. He was of a middle ſtature, brown, and ſomething too Corpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. He was as brave as one could be: Of a kind diſpoſition: His Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling paſſion was love, and one of the beſt Princes that ever Reigned. A diſpenſation was obtained from the Pope for his marrying the Queen Widdow of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> formerly known in <hi>France</hi> by the name of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150241:7"/>Princeſs <hi>Mary.</hi> He had ever had an eſteem for her, and for her part ſhe had likewiſe very much conſidered him: Inſomuch that they were not much troubled to change the names of Brother and Siſter for thoſe of Husband and Wife, tho the example was ſomthing rare. The good of the State ſerved for a pretext to the real inclination they had a long time had for one another. The Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of their Marriage were hardly finiſhed, than that the troubles which were newly appeaſed began again in the Kingdom, thro a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular quarrel of a <hi>Poliſh</hi> Gentleman, with <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> General of the <hi>Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aques.</hi> Thoſe people are compoſed of ſeveral ſtrangers, and principal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Peaſants, who to deliver themſelves from the ſlavery of the Nobles have abandoned their Country to retire into the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>kraine,</hi> a Province bordering upon the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> and <hi>Turkes,</hi> and abounding in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150241:7"/>all that is neceſſary to life. They are of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Religion under the obedience of a Patriarch, whoſe Reſidence is at <hi>Kiof,</hi> a very fair and large City, Governed under the Authority of the King of <hi>Poland.</hi> The <hi>Coſaques</hi> being obliged to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the entrance of the Kingdom againſt the Infidels, they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Armed when they work, that they may not be ſurprized, and without taking any pay of the King or the Republick, they ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly expoſe their lives, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenting themſelves with the booty only that they take from the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Crown. They are very affectionate to the King, but their hatred againſt the Nobles is ſo great, that the leaſt quarrels obliges them to take Armes and to revenge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves cruelly for the offences they receive. They have never any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leader to Command them than ſuch as they have choſen amongſt
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150241:8"/>themſelves: And tho he were but a Shepherd, provided he be brave and fortunate in fight, they obey him very exactly and have for him a great reſpect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> their General was the Son of a Miller, but the Victor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ies he gained over the <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> rendered him ſo illuſtrious, that he paſſed for one of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Captains of the age. After the Death of his Father having demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of King <hi>Caſimer</hi> leave to build up again the Mill that his Father had left him, and of adding to it ſome Houſes for the Honouring his Memory, it was granted to him in conſideration of his Merit and the ſervices he had done him and the Republick. <hi>Jarinski</hi> a <hi>Poliſh</hi> Colonel oppoſed <hi>Chilmilenski</hi>'s de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, and forbid him to paſs far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſaying that the Water of his Mill incommoded him, that the King commanded upon his own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150241:8"/>Lands and he upon his. But theſe haughty words not having at all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged <hi>Chilmilenski,</hi> the Colonel in his abſence cauſed his Mill and Houſes to be burnt, and miſuſed his Wife and his Son who would have hindered him. It is eaſie to imagine what impreſſion this outrage made in the Soul of that great Man. He promiſed no leſs to his revenge than the exterminating all the Nobility, and his Courage ſo well ſeconded him, that having raiſed a powerful Army, he ruined all the Nobles, on one ſide as far as <hi>Lublin,</hi> and thro all <hi>Podolia</hi> as far, as <hi>Ruſtemburg.</hi> Women and Children were no more ſpared than the Churches, and thoſe whom fire and Sword had left, were ſold to the <hi>Turkes;</hi> inſomuch that for the burning of a Mill ſixty Cities were deſtroyed. The Senators of the Kingdom, without whom the King undertakes nothing that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Republick, beſeeched him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150241:9"/>to Arme for the deſtroying the <hi>Coj<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aques,</hi> but the King refuſed them, ſaying that it was their fault, and that <hi>Jarinski</hi> ought not to have burnt <hi>Chilmilenski</hi>'s Mill. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this refuſal the Nobility compoſed an Army of fifty thouſand men, and marched directly to the <hi>Coſaques,</hi> who expected them in good order. The Battail was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. The <hi>Polanders</hi> loſt it, and ten thouſand of them were killed upon the place. The Runaways were purſued more than twelve Leagues, and the <hi>Coſaques</hi> loaden with ſpoiles and Glory returned to their homes, deſtroying all the places thro which they paſſed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Lands belonging to the King.</p>
            <p>The Nobles irritated with this great loſs, and breathing nothing but vengeance, made a Convocation of the ſeventh man, which is called in the language of their Country
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150241:9"/>
               <hi>Poſpolite Ruſſin,</hi> and having joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome <hi>German</hi> Troops to that levy, they renewed the War contrary to the Kings ſentiment, who coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled them to agree, becauſe that the <hi>Coſaques</hi> defended the Kingdom againſt the invaſion of Infidels. But inſtead of following this good advice, the King became ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, tho he went himſelf to command their Army.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Coſaques</hi> having notice of theſe preparations, took the field with fifty thouſand men, and their ſpies having informed them that the <hi>Polanders</hi> were encamped beyond the <hi>Nieper,</hi> and were not upon their Guard, relying on their great Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, they paſſed ſecretly the River one Night, and having ſurprized the Enemies they killed ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of them upon the place, put the reſt into diſorder, and perſued them as far as <hi>Zamoſh,</hi> took all the baggage and four and twenty pieces
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150241:10"/>of Canon, which they ſent to <hi>Kiof</hi> for a mark of their Victory; and having laid feige to the City after the Trenches having been opened a Month, they became Maſters of it. <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> by theſe great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages having made himſelf formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable, propoſed to the Duke of <hi>Walachia</hi> an offenſive League a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Poland,</hi> and the Marriage of his Son with the Dukes Daughter; but there being ſome difficulty made in it, whether becauſe of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equality of their conditions, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that having married his Eldeſt Daughter to Prince <hi>Radezivil,</hi> he could not quit the party of the <hi>Polan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Chilmilenski</hi> threatned to drive him out of his ſtates: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that for the avoiding of the War, the Duke conſented to the Marriage, upon condition that after the Death of <hi>Chilmilenski,</hi> his Son ſhould ſucceed in the Generalſhip; which was granted him by all the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150241:10"/>
               <hi>Coſaques.</hi> The <hi>Polanders</hi> having notice of the day that the Nuptials were to be celebrated, drew up with deſigne to trouble the Feaſt, well imagining that the <hi>Coſaques</hi> would not be upon their Guard. In truth, theſe not dreaming of any thing but Mirth, were ſurprized in the City of <hi>Kiof,</hi> which the <hi>Polanders</hi> ruined without much trouble. The Nobles who were detained Priſoners there, were freed, the <hi>Greek</hi> Churches deſtroyed and pillaged, the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch carryed away priſoner, and the <hi>Coſaques</hi> were ſo weakned by this unexpected blow, that they appeared to be in the extreameſt conſternation. Being however re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered from their aſtoniſhment, they ſent an Ambaſſador to the King, to demand of him if it was by his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that action had been done, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending their Patriach ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored them, and a reparation made them proportionable to their loſs.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150241:11"/>The King having anſwered that Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador that he had neither order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chilmilenski</hi>'s Mill ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, nor that the City of <hi>Kiof</hi> ſhould be ruined, but that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility had done it of their own moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to recompence themſelves for their loſſes; the <hi>Coſaques</hi> joyned themſelves to the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred <hi>Podolia,</hi> committing all the Hoſtilities that War inſpires deſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate people with. The Nobles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing acquainted with this new irrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, told the King plainly, that if he did not march at their head, they would have recourſe to <hi>Ragoski</hi> Duke of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> and chooſe him in his ſtead. The King, who had reaſon to apprehend it, and who had a long time known their ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, promiſed to march with the <hi>German</hi> Trops; with which they were not pleaſed, becauſe they would have had them mingled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. In fine the Army
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150241:11"/>came to <hi>Cantinitz Podolski,</hi> which is a very ſtrong City, where after ſeveral little rencounters, was ſought a bloody Battail, wherein the <hi>Coſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques</hi> were beaten, being conſtrained to flie. But as they had made their Magazines in the Marſhes, and that they expected ſuccour, they retired thither, and the <hi>Palanders</hi> believing that they ſhould infallibly Periſh there, blocked up the <hi>Caſaques,</hi> whoſe ſuccours being arrived they cut off from the <hi>Polanders</hi> all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage for Victuals, and conſtrained them to make immediately a diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious Peace. This Peace was not ſigned, inſomuch that <hi>Caſimer</hi> retired to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> and the Nobles to their Houſes, extreat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly humbled by their great loſſes, and very ill ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with him, accuſing him of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voring the <hi>Coſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ques.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The King having a tender Soul, and being no longer poſſeſſed with thoughts of War, Love appeared
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150241:12"/>to him more agreeable. The Vice-Chancellor <hi>Ragieski,</hi> had for ſome few years been Married to a young Lady whoſe Beauty had made a great deal of noiſe at Court. She was in her two and twentieth year, of a middle Stature, but very well Carriaged, her Eyes were black, full and well turned, and whoſe Luſter and ſweetneſs inſpired affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in all who ſaw her, her Noſe well made, her mouth pretty, and all parts of her face ſo well propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, that having therewith a Wit very gay and Gallant, few perſons have been ſeen more accompliſhed. The Vice-Chancellor uſually kept her at a Countrey Houſe near <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw,</hi> as it is the Cuſtom of all the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Lords, whoſe Wives go ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to Court, giving them a kind of Governeſſe for to watch over their actions when civility obliges them to bring them thither. The Reputation of the Vice-Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150241:12"/>Lady had given the King that preſſing deſire that one has of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſons whoſe Beauty is famous, and her preſence at Court ſo well compleated what her Reputation had begun, that he became infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in love. He felt in his heart all thoſe violent motions which we uſually are ſenſible of at the birth of great paſſions; but this violence ſo agreeably deprived him of his liberty, that without conſidering he ſhould have a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand obſtacles to conquer, he aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned himſelf without referve to the power of that Lady. There are Kings who are ſo made that they need only to ſpeak to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves beloved, but <hi>Caſimer</hi> was not of this Number, and his power did not reach ſo far. He feared the Queen, and he knew to what ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes the <hi>Polanders</hi> proceed when they are jealous. Wherefore he contented himſelf to ſhow in the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150241:13"/>ning more complaiſance to the Vice-Chancellours Wife than to the other Ladies of the Court, and ſometimes fixing his looks upon her they made her clearly ſee what hers had produced in his heart. But his paſſion was too violent to remain long in ſilence. The Baron <hi>de Saint-Cir,</hi> a French Gentleman, had been ſome years at the Court of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> his good meen, his wit, his conduct and his Bravery had acquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him the Reputation of a very Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant man. He often ſaw the Vice-Chancellour <hi>Ragieski,</hi> who ſeemed to be much his friend, and the King who naturally loved all the French, honoured him alſo with a particular eſteem, whether for his merit, or that he was a Relation of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſe <hi>des Roches</hi> the Governeſſe of the Queens Maids of Honour, who had a great kindneſs for him. All theſe conſiderations obliged the King to chooſe him to be the later<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150241:13"/>of his Love, and to deceive the foreſight of thoſe whoſe intereſt it was to traverſe him. Wherefore he cauſed him to come one day into his Cabinet, where after having gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him new marks of his bounty, he gave him in charge to make known his Sentiments to the Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours Lady, declaring to him of what importance it was for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Tho the Commiſſion was nice, the Baron knowing the jeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous humour of <hi>Ragieski,</hi> he made no difficulty of accepting it; and of telling the King that he eſteemed himſelf ſo happy in the Honour that he did him by truſting him with ſo important a ſecret, that he ſhould willingly ſacrifice his life to render his Majeſty all the ſervice he was capable of. The King, who expected no leſs from the Barons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, promiſed to make him a Royal acknowledgment, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing immediately took the Meaſures
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150241:14"/>they judged neceſſary for the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding well in this enterprize, which was to be ſo fatal to <hi>Caſimer,</hi> and all the Kingdom; the Baron re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to his apartment to think of it at leaſure. As he had the liberty of going often to <hi>Ragieski</hi>'s Houſe, he applyed himſelf more particularly than he had done before to ſhow kindneſs to all thoſe of the Family, and having an inſinuating and an agreeable wit, he became ſo much in the favour of her who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a Governeſſe to the Vice-Chancellours Lady, that being enarmed with his Civilities, ſhe was mighty complaiſant to him. He took occaſion to ſpeak often of the King and then exaggerated his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality, his tenderneſs, his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and his other great Qualities, in terms ſo advantagious that it made this Woman deſirous of try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them. After having thus diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her mind, he cunningly made the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150241:14"/>Vice-Chancellours Lady obſerve the earneſtneſs the King was in of ſeeing her when ſhe was at Court; and even ſometimes told her ſmil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that he believed ſhe had made him her conqueſt: and he ſo often repeated it to her in the preſence of her Governeſſe, that being fair and having no leſs ambition than Beauty, he remarked that it did not at all diſpleaſe her. He informed the King thereof, who redoubled his cares. The Lady perceived it with joy, and the Baron having made the Governeſſe his conſident in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, who fancied her fortune was thereby made, they reſolved toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that the King ſhould write to her that he might explain himſelf more preciſely. The Governeſſe promiſed to do her devoir, and ſome days after the King wrote to the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in theſe termes.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150241:15"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Love you, Madam, and this ought not to ſurprize you. You are ſo Beautiful that it is impoſſible long to reſiſt your Charmes: and in what Elevation ſoever we are one is very glad to wear your chaines. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore try if you pleaſe, Madam, the moſt ſincere paſſion that ever was. Let not my greatneſs give you any ombrage; and ſurmount as I have done all the vain ſeruples which might hinder as from becoming happy, ſince never Prince was more diſereet, than</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CASIMER.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Baron having taken an occaſion of ſpeaking in particular to the Vice-Chancellours Lady, gave her the Letter that the King ſent her. She changed colour ſeveral times as ſhe read it, and there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſuch an alteration in her face, that he looked upon it as a good au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150241:15"/>however after having read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſhe ſaid nothing more to him, than that ſhe was very much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to the King for the Honour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he did her, and that ſhe had no anſwer to make. The Baron would have ſpoke to her, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality coming in, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired and went to give an account to <hi>Caſimer</hi> of what he had done. This Prince was ſo ſatisfied with what he acquainted him, tho he could not fix any certainty, that after having told him the moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging things he could have hoped, he preſented him with a Diamond of great value. While that the King flattered himſelf agreeably with the hopes of being beloved, ſhe for her part felt agitations that were not uſual to her; and calling back into her memory all thoſe obliging and paſſionate looks by which he explained himſelf when ſhe was at Court, ſhe did not at all doubt of her
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150241:16"/>Conqueſt. But his Letter ſo poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively aſſured her, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the confiderations which ought to have diſcouraged her, ſhe took a delight in believing it. <hi>Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> was as well made as <hi>Ragieski,</hi> tho a King, ſhe was young, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to be diſcreet and faithful, all this very much ſhaked her mind, and ſhe became more thoughtful than ſhe uſed to be. Her Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe who was not ignorant of the cauſe, asked her however the occaſion of her Melancholy. She excuſed her ſelf a long time from telling it her, but ſhe preſſed her to it after ſo engaging a manner, and with ſo many Proteſtations of ſerving her faithfully, that ſhe could not reſiſt any longer. She embraced her ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and after having told her that the happineſs of her life con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted in keeping the ſecret ſhe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted to her, ſhe ſhowed her the Kings Letter. The Governeſſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150241:16"/>to be ſurprized, ſhe read it ſeriouſly, and having remonſtrated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o the Lady the danger ſhe expoſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſelf to by the noiſe that this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion would make in the world, ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen ſpoke to her in ſo advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s a manner of the Kings tenderneſs, that after having eyed her with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind of compaſſion, ſhe promiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o manage things ſo cunningly, that there needed no more to determine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to receive favourably his Vows. Whereupon going to Court in the Evening, the King explaining to her as his cuſtome was the condition his Soul was in ſhe anſwered him ſo obligingly, that he did not at all doubt but that he ſhould be happy. He appeared on the ſuddain in the gayeſt humour imaginable, and without ſhowing any affectation he approached the Vice-Chancellours Lady, to whom he reiterated the Proteſtations he had made her in his Letter of loving her Eternally. That
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150241:17"/>Charming perſon whom the King diſcourſe cauſed to bluſh, replyed with a great deal of Modeſty and ſweetneſs. It is ſo little credible Sir, that you can be in the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you would perſwade us, that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I could flatter my ſelf that a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prince as you are could love ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I ſhould take a ſenſible delight i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your paſſion: But, Sir, ſo many things oblige me not to add Faith to your words, that I dare not tell you I could wiſh they were real. How agreeable was this Confeſſion to the King! His joy made him for a long time immovable, and then of a ſuddain that ſame joy having fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed him with the Eloquence o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſatisfied Lovers, the Proteſtatoin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Oaths that he made to that La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy perfectly conquered her. It wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thus they were engaged, there wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> nothing more wanting to complea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their happineſs, than the finding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> convenient place to entertain on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:150241:17"/>another without witneſſes. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince gave order to the Baron to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ak thereof to the Vice-Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours Lady. But as he was endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouring it, and that the King expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with impatience that happy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he was obliged to go into the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mpagne</hi> to defend himſelf againſt the Invaſion of the Great Duke of <hi>Moſcovy,</hi> who without any reaſon broak the Peace that King <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> had made with him. That Prince aſſiſted by the <hi>Coſaques</hi> took the City of <hi>Smolensko,</hi> and they made ſuch other conſiderable Progreſſes in <hi>Lithuania,</hi> that the ruine of the Kingdom was with reaſon appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended. <hi>Caſimer</hi> cauſed of his own proper motion ſuccours to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of the Duke of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> of the <hi>Hoſpidars,</hi> of the <hi>Tartars</hi> and of the other people of thoſe Countries; but all theſe Forces not being equal to thoſe of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, he could not hinder the ruin
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150241:18"/>of <hi>Vilna</hi> the Capital City of <hi>Lithu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ania;</hi> all perſons there above fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years old were put to the Sword, and the reſt were carried to <hi>Moſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> to be brought up there in the <hi>Greek</hi> Religion. It is eaſie to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agine the deplorable Condition theſe ſad Conjunctures put the King in. He loved his people tenderly, but he loved his Miſtreſs more; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that one may ſay that never was Prince agitated with ſo many paſſions at a time. The Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours Lady was no more at eaſe than he, for he begun to be dear to her: She apprehended the loſing him amongſt the hazards of War, or that abſence might diminiſh the paſſion he had ſhowed her before his departure. All that the Baron could ſay to her to aſſure her of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary did not ſatisfie her: And if the Winter had not brought the King back to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> that fair per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon would not have been able to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150241:18"/>have concealed any longer, the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure ſhe had in Her mind. But all theſe Clouds were diſſipated at the moment they ſaw one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther again; the King neglected the ſares of War, to think of nothing but pleaſing that Lady; and ſhe likewiſe abandoned her ſelf to the motions of her Paſſion, after a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo obliging to him, that he had nothing more to wiſh for, than the vanquiſhing a weak reſiſtance. They enjoyed for ſome time, all the ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pleaſures that a blooming paſſion uſually gives; and Love took care of baniſhing from their minds, all the ill humours and diſquiets that might traverſe their contentment. But whether that <hi>Ragieski</hi> had perceived any thing, or that the neceſſity of his affairs obliged him to go into the Country, he carried his Lady thither, and departed ſo ſuddainly from <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw,</hi> that ſhe had not time of bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Adieu to any body. <hi>Caſimer</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:150241:19"/>was not a little aſtoniſhed when he was told the news of it; he had in his mind all that Choler could inſpire the moſt furious with; he vowed the ruin of the Vice-Chancellour, and in fine became ſo out of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, that all the Court perceived it, each One endeavouring to pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate into it's Cauſe; The Baron was the only One that knew it, and it was to him alone he diſcovered his moſt ſecret thoughts, and to whom in the firſt tranſports of his grief, he ſaid the moſt touching things imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. But as this violent Condition could not laſt long, and that the Vice-Chancellour's Houſe was not far diſtant from <hi>Warſaw;</hi> the Baron in ſome manner eaſed the Kings ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, in giving him hopes, that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of hunting he might procure him an interview with his Miſtreſs, and adding to that, that he ſhould likewiſe find the Conveniency of conveying to her his Letters, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150241:19"/>receiving of her Anſwers with ſafety; He ſeemed ſatisfied, and left to him the care of mannaging the buſineſs. The Vice-Chancellor kept a breed of Race Horſes in his Park; he had ſeveral times deſired the Baron, who underſtood riding very well, to go ſee his Horſes; he took that time to ſatisfie him, and to deliver to his Lady a Letter the King had given him in Charge. <hi>Ragieski</hi> received the Baron with a great deal of joy; but his Lady ſaw him with much more, ſhe needed him for the dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing the grief that the Kings abſence cauſed in her: And when the Baron had given her the Kings Letter, ſhe recovered her good humour: It was in theſe terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MAy I ask you, Madam, what has obliged you to quitt me ſo promptly? But how could you do it without bidding me Adieu? do not you very well know that being the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150241:20"/>Love of all men, it was to abandon me to all the greateſt Cruelties one could ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in the World? Return hither Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, and bring back the joy and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which have followed you, or let what will happen I will go ſee you: Life is inſupportable to me, when you are abſent, and never any one loved more paſſionately, than</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CASIMER.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Vice-Chancellor's Lady, who went into the Country againſt her will, was in no leſs pain there, than the King at <hi>Warſaw;</hi> and her paſſion for him was come to that point, that <hi>Ragieski</hi> ſeeing her in an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary melancholy, begun to obſerve her more ſtrictly, to endeavour to diſcover its cauſe, and even preſſed her very often to tell it him; But as his importunities augmented her ill humour; the Baron came very conveniently to remove it, and <hi>Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi>'s
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150241:20"/>Letter diſperſed all her fears: She' had at the leaſt as much impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience as he to be at <hi>Warſaw;</hi> ſhe pretended to be ſick that ſhe might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn thither. But <hi>Ragieski</hi> not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving the diſeaſe very preſſing, ſtill delayed his departure. In the mean time ſhe paſſionately longed to ſee the King, and yet ſhe apprehended his impatience would make him come, becauſe that her Husband would have certainly diſcovered their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce. In this uncertainty a middle way was to be found out. There was a very fine houſe two Leagues from theirs, belonging to an Officer of the Crown; the Baron propoſed to the Vice-Chancellor's Lady to make a party for hunting there, where he would cauſe the King to come; ſhe approved the expedient, and as nothing is impoſſible to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of wit, ſhe ſo well mannaged the buſineſs that <hi>Ragieski</hi> himſelf pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the Baron the hunting a
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150241:21"/>Stag two days after: for the better concealing his deſign, he pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have buſineſs which obliged him to return. This cauſed his ſtay to be the more preſſed, and all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus reſolved, he wrote to the King, marking preciſely the Place where he might ſee the Vice-Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors Lady; and that he might add faith to his words, ſhe wrote him this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOu know I love you Sir, and it is enough to perſwade you that I was brought hither againſt my will. But is it true that you endure as much as you ſay? Ah <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>af it be ſo, I have reaſon to be contented with the trouble your abſence cauſes me. But why ſhould you deceive me? Ought not my tenderneſs to aſſure me of yours? And why ſhould not you ſuffer? Come then Sir, to the place ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, and beleive that beſides the pleaſure of hunting, you will likewiſe have there the pleaſute of Jeaing the perſon of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150241:21"/>the world, the moſt really</hi> Yours.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Baron gave this Letter to his Gentleman of the Horſe, to carry it to the King. But tho the ſucceſs of his voyage ought to have given him a great deal of joy, as he paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately loved the <hi>Marchioneſs das Reches,</hi> whoſe abſence made him in an extream pain, he could not help ſhowing his uneaſineſs: <hi>Ragieski</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leiving that the Baron was weary of his houſe, did all he could to divert him; and ſeeing that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Careſſes and his good Treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſtill reſerved ſo great a Melancholy that he could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal it, he fancyed him to be in Love, he had already rallied him upon that point ſeveral times at <hi>Warſaw,</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſo aſſiduous with the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs des Roches</hi> his Relation. But tho they were often together, he had never made him his Confident. Wherefore he renewed his earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150241:22"/>in ſo civil and galant a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that the Baron did really avow to him his paſſion. <hi>Ragieski</hi> beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing there muſt needs be ſomthing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary in their intrigue, obliged the Baron to make him the recital of it, and after having promiſed ſecrecy, the thing being of conſequence e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, the Baron thus began his Hiſtory.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:150241:22"/>
            <head>THE <hi>HISTORY</hi> OF THE <hi>Baron</hi> de SAINT-CIR.</head>
            <p>DUring the laſt Civil wars which cauſed ſo much diſorder in <hi>France,</hi> my Father who is of one of the beſt Families of <hi>Guyenne,</hi> ſent me to <hi>Paris,</hi> where the Queen Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> kept her Court. I was then four and twenty years old, and tho I had not all the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary qualities to make me be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed in the fineſt Court of the world, I dare however affirm that in a little time I procured a great many Friends. As I had ever had a great
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150241:23"/>paſſion to ſee <hi>Italy,</hi> and that my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had hindred me from it, becauſe that I was the only Son, and he loved me tenderly, it was with a great deal of trouble that he conſented to my making that voyage. But after having taken all the neceſſary mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures for the ſatisfying my curioſity: One day as I went to the <hi>Louvre,</hi> to take leave of a friend of mine, a perſon of Quality; I met a young Lady, who being left a Widdow without Children, ſaw her ſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to diſpute with the Heirs of her deceaſed Husband, a piece of land of great value that he had given her at his Death: Her ſhape being of the moſt advantagious, cauſed me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſtop to conſider it; I felt in my heart ſo great a deſire of knowing nor, that I could not hold from fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing her; ſhe being deirous to preſent a Petition to the Queen and to beg her Protection, ſhe adreſſed her ſelf to the Captain of the Guards,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150241:23"/>who was the ſame I was alſo look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for: Love being reſolved to make me feel its darts, would make uſe of that Occaſion to learn me his Laws; for the <hi>Marchioneſs des Roches</hi> (thus was that Lady called) made the recital of her affans, in ſo witty and galant a manner, that being likewiſe as you know very pretty, I intereſſed my ſelf in her affairs, as if ſhe had been very conſider able to me. I forgot the deſign I had made of travelling, and believing that I could never do any thing more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greable or advantageous to my ſelf, than to make my applications to that fair Widdow: I thought of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o thing but the means I ſhould make uſe of for the acquainting her with my ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents: Wherefore after having thought a while, I in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> the Marchioneſs, whom I had ſtill eyed very attentively, for to cell my friend, that tho I was perſwaded that his Generoſity would inſallib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y move
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150241:24"/>him to ſerve her, I however joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Prayers to hers, and conjured him to employ his Credit, and to procure her a favourable Audience of the Queen. And then addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing my ſelf to her, I told her, with an air that made apparent the part I took in what concerned her. I could not hope, Madam, to be happy enough to offer my ſervices to ſo lovely a perſon as you, but ſince my good fortune has given me ſome part in my Lord's friendſhip, I could not let this occaſion paſs without teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to you, in recommending to him your intereſts, the extream paſſion I have of ſerving you; and I ſhould heartily deſire, Madam, that time would furniſh me with more favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Ones, that I might the better make appear, the zeal and reſpect I have for your Ladyſhip. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, whom theſe words cauſed to bluſh, anſwered me with a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty that perfectly charmed me
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150241:24"/>lought, without doubt, my Lord, to attribute to your generoſity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, the obliging offers you make me; for not knowing in my ſelf any quality that might procure me ſo galant a man as you for Protector, I ſhould be very vain to believe that my merit had engaged you to take ſo much part in my intereſts; and Heaven, that always protects afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons, muſt needs have ſent you on purpoſe hither, to give me marke of your goodneſs. While we were thus diſcourſing, an Officer came and informed us that the Queen was going out, the Captain gave his hand to the Marchioneſs to preſent her to her Majeſty; ſhe was received very favourably, and after that the Queen was mounted into the Coach, I did all that I could to accompany the Marchioneſs to her houſe, but ſhe would not conſent to it; Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that I returned to my houſe with ſentiments very oppoſite to
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150241:25"/>theſe that had brought me to the <hi>Louvre Paris</hi> ſeemed to me a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times more charming than I had ever found it, and felt my ſelf ſo taken with the Beauties of the Marchioneſs, that I entirely renounced the deſire of travelling, to think only of the means of pleaſing her. Love, to be well received in fouls, enters them uſually attended with graces and joys, that he may the more eaſily Maſter them, repreſented to me the Marchioneſs as the moſt lovely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the world, in making me ſometimes remar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue with pleaſure that ſweetneſs which accompanies all her actions, and then the vivacity of her Wit, and that galant turn ſhe gives to things; inſomuch that never having been in that condition, I admired ſo extraordinary a change, having thus made ſeveral reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon my adventure, I went to bed, thinking to ſleep; but I had hardly ſhut my Eyes to abandon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150241:25"/>my ſelf to ſleep, that that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs repreſented her ſelf to my fancy, with yet more Charms than I had found in her. I awaked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my cuſtom which ſurprized me, and after having in vain endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to fall aſleep again, I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed thus to my ſelf: Whence proceeds it that in a moment all my Curioſity is vaniſhed? I have no longer that ſtrong paſſion which has ſo long tormented me; and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for one time ſeeing the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs <hi>des Roches,</hi> I find my ſelf diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted and penſive: What will it then be when I ſhall know her more particularly? No, no, I'le have no engagement with a perſon who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces ſo extraordinary effects, the Conſequences would be too fatal to my repoſe, and I ſhould deprive my ſelf of the thing I eſteem the moſt in the world: Wherefore He depart and remove my ſelf from theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before I'le be engaged; Neither
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150241:26"/>can I well juſtifie a delay of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to my Father, or all my friends, of whom I have taken leave. But alas what do I ſay! to go from <hi>Paris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> my heart cannot conſent to it, what I ſhould leave there is more worth than all the reſt of the Univerſe. My fair Widdow, ought to be to me inſtead of all my voyages, and I ſhall take an extream pleaſure in ſeeing her, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſhe will not be inſenſible to my Vows, and that in fine I ſhall be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py enough not to diſpleaſe her. Let none talk to me any more of travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, I have loſt the thoughts of it; and ſince we muſt once loſe our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, and become ſlaves, Ah! may it be the adorable Marchioneſs, who has not her like. Having be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides made ſeveral other Reflections, it was impoſſible for me to ſleep: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the day being far ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced without any of my ſervants having been in my Chamber, one of my friends who was ſurprized to ſee
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150241:26"/>me ſo long in Bed, came by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence to interrupt my privacies: and as he had a great power over me, he asked me what obliged me to be ſo lazy, ſeeing I had not too much time for the giving order for my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, and having anſwered him that I had been very much indiſpoſed all the night, but that I found my ſelf ſomthing better; I roſe preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, and went to the Palace of <hi>Orleans,</hi> to trie by the Beauty of thoſe gardens, to divert the troubles this budding paſſion gave me: But inſtead of finding there the Remedy I ſought, after having walked thro with little application all theſe fine walks, <hi>I</hi> was the more confirmed of fixing my ſelf in the ſervice of the Marchioneſs, and <hi>I</hi> returned home ſo penſive, that <hi>I</hi> found no pleaſure but in the agreeable Idea <hi>I</hi> preſerved of her Beauty: Inſomuch that two days after <hi>I</hi> went to make her my firſt viſit, and as our converſation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150241:27"/>was pretty long, <hi>I</hi> had time to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the delicacy of her wit. She ſaid the fineſt things imaginable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the point of our acquaintance, and <hi>I</hi> returned ſo ſatisfied with the Marchioneſſes Civility, and ſo much charmed with her, that Love had never been better eſtabliſhed in a heart. <hi>I</hi> began from that time to take more care of my perſon than I had done, <hi>I</hi> became more penſive than uſual, and all that was nor the Marchioneſs ſeemed to me ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, that even my friends perceived me to be changed. But the time <hi>I</hi> had taken to depart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed as well as my curioſity, <hi>I</hi> feigned an indiſpoſition, of which <hi>I</hi> gave notice to my Father, who having with pain conſented <hi>I</hi> ſhould travel, was very glad to hear <hi>I</hi> was no longer in haſt to leave the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and as he had a deſign of buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing me a conſiderable Charge at Court, helet me know it was his
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150241:27"/>will I ſhould ſtay there. It is eaſie to imagine the joy this news gave me, as it agreed with my Love; never any thing was more welcome; and having then no other paſſion than of ſerving the Marchioneſs, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aw her dayly, and loſt no occaſion of making known to her my paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. All the difficulty was to make her ſee I loved her; my languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eyes, and redoubled ſighs made it apparent that I was not inſenſible: But all this did not ſatisfie me, and when I went from her I could not bear with any company: And when alone I paſſed over in my mind, all that I had ſaid, and all that I had done; ſometimes I blamed my ſelf for having been too fearful, and then again for having been too bold. And I was ever as ill contented with my ſelf, as I was fatisfied with that lovely perſon. In fine time furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me with an occaſion which <hi>I</hi> made uſe of luckily enough. The
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150241:28"/>Marchioneſs had a friend who was often in our Company, and who having ſome inclination for me, did all ſhe could to diſcover her for whom <hi>I</hi> ſighed, and even preſſed me ſo agreably upon that point, that <hi>I</hi> was put to much trouble to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal my paſſion. One day as we went all three of us to walk in the Gardens, the Marchioneſs and <hi>I</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly fixing languiſhing looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one another, that friend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it, told me with great ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, Ah! Sir, <hi>I</hi> know at preſent what you have concealed from me with ſo much care, and then held her peace and would ſay no more. We did all that we could to break her ſilence, and eſpecially the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs preſſed her to tell her the cauſe of it, but all was in vain: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that not being willing to ſtay any longer in the Gardens, we were conſtrained to return. Tho the Marchioneſs had not had the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150241:28"/>curioſity that is natural to the ſex, this Myſtery would have given it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er: Wherefore making her a viſit the day after, ſhe did not fail as ſoon as ſhe ſaw me to preſs me to diſcover the ſecret, well imagining I was there for ſomething. As I knew not preciſely its cauſe, <hi>I</hi> found my ſelf perplexed, <hi>I</hi> did all that <hi>I</hi> could to defend my ſelf from telling my thoughts; But as in thoſe ſort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f occaſions, the more we excuſe our ſelves from telling Ladies what they would learn, the more it aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments their Curioſity; the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs redoubled her earneſtneſs, and would abſolutely know my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion thereof: Inſomuch that that Conjuncture ſeeming to me very favourable for the diſcovering to her my paſſion, <hi>I</hi> tried two or three times to tell her what <hi>I</hi> had reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, but <hi>I</hi> found in that moment the Power of an amourous reſpect, and it was with a great deal of fear
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150241:29"/>and Confuſion, that with a trembl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voice <hi>I</hi> told her, that her friend had perceived <hi>I</hi> loved her, and that it had put her into ſo ill an humou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Yes, Madam, added <hi>I,</hi> it is impoſſibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to love you more, and if you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er what your Charms are able to effect, you would eaſily judge they cannot but produce extraordinary paſſions. The Marchioneſs expecting to learn quite the contrary, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ſurprized to hear me ſpeak ſo ſeriouſly; ſhe was upon the point of being angry, of baniſhing me from her preſence: But having preſſed me to declare my thoughts, ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented her ſelf with telling me, with a tone however that ſhewed her agitation: if <hi>I</hi> had been leſs cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ertain, Sir, you would not have taken the liberty of ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to me after the manner you have done, and that the reſpect you owe to our Sex would have hindred you: but ſince <hi>I</hi> my ſelf have occaſioned
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150241:29"/>this fault, I will not puniſh you as <hi>I</hi> might otherwiſe have done; and if you deſire we ſhall ſee one another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gain, <hi>I</hi> pretend it be without paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and <hi>I</hi> forbid you to tell me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain you have any for me: Theſe words having ſomething encouraged me, and not being ignorant, that when it is once ſaid We, love, Love repeats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a thouſand times; <hi>I</hi> turned the thing galantly, in ſaying to the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs, that ſhe had obliged me more than ſhe thought in forbidding me to ſpeak of my paſſion, ſeeing <hi>I</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not expreſs it well enough by words, and that it was impoſſible to explain the ſentiments of a heart ſo much in love as mine. That <hi>I</hi> would obey her and keep ſilence; but that <hi>I</hi> hoped my Eyes, and all my actions would ſo well ſupply the defect of my tongue, that at length ſhe would be perſwaded that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could be added to the reſpectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous and ſincere affection <hi>I</hi> had for
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150241:30"/>her; <hi>I</hi> had hardly done ſpeaking, when the Marchioneſs's Companion entred the Chamber: But the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs being ill ſatisfied with her Curioſity, ſhe was careful not to ask her alſo the reaſon of her Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly; inſomuch that the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation falling upon general and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things, it quickly finiſhed, each one retiring. From that time I had ſome kindof hopes the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs would hear my Vows, and as hopes flatter and eaſe the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Lovers, <hi>I</hi> almoſt ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted to my advantage all ſhe ſaid to me. But it was not how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever till after a years aſſiduity, that that fair Perſon let her ſelf be van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed, and that ſhe gave me all the marks of eſteem and kindneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>I</hi> could have expected from a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in whom Vertue was in the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premeſt Degree. Never was ſo pure and innocent a paſſion ſeen as tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we had, nor did ever Lovers paſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:150241:30"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir time ſo ſweetly as we did du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ſome Months. But theſe fine lays were eclipſed, and Love made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e know that if he lends for a time is joys and favours, he pays him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lf with Uſury. The Marchioneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s merit being known by all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons of Judgment, it happened to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y misfortune that a Lady of great Quality having been deſired by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>een of <hi>Poland,</hi> to ſend her a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rench Lady to be Governeſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Maids of Honour, ſhe caſt her Eyes upon the Marchioneſs, and ſo well perſwaded her of the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance of that employ, that at length <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e reſolved to accept it. Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is natural to the ſex, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her in that moment the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt paſſion; ſhe imagined I would with joy ſubſcribe to her abſence, and that I even would follow her; and in that opinion ſhe ſecretly took all the neceſſary meaſures for her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, being reſolved I ſhould not
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150241:31"/>know it till the day before. But a ill News is ever learnt ſooner tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one would know it, I had noti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> given me of the Marchioneſſes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. Never was a ſurprize equ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to mine, and as if <hi>I</hi> had been ſtruc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with a thunder-bolt, <hi>I</hi> was a lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> time immoveable without being ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſpeak one word. At length re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> covering my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> examined all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed Conduct, to ſee if <hi>I</hi> had do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any thing that might oblige the Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> chioneſs to treat me thus, and afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> having exactly recollected to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very leaſt Circumſtances, findin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf only guilty of too muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Love, <hi>I</hi> accuſed her a thouſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> times of injuſtice and infidelity and then referring my caſe to Lov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf, <hi>I</hi> made him the Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my misfortunes, and my diſorde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſo great that <hi>I</hi> did not ſpa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my ſelf: Inſomuch that after havi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> taken a hundred ſeveral Reſolu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the breaking of this voy
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150241:31"/>age, things even the moſt extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant came into my imagination, and all agitated with different paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; <hi>I</hi> went to the Marchioneſs to reproach her with her inconſtancy: but <hi>I</hi> had no ſooner ſeen her, than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat Love recovering the Empire of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y heart, as faithleſs as ſhe was, <hi>I</hi> found her with the ſame Charms as formerly. All my Reſolutions va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and if the Marchioneſs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>receiving grief in my face, had not asked me what cauſed it, <hi>I</hi> ſhould not have been able to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained of my misfortune, ſo true is it that it is impoſſible when one loves very tenderly, to be able to reproach the beloved Object, Whom we ever excuſe through a kind of ſhame of ſeeing our ſelves deceived, or for fear of diſpleaſing. Whereupon the Marchioneſs acquainted me with the reaſons ſhe had to accept the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers that were made her, and Love made me find them to be the beſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150241:32"/>imaginable, during all the time was with her: Inſomuch that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Marchioneſs ſeeing her ſelf free<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from this dangerous point, fancye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhe ſhould certainly take that vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> age, and was poſſeſſed with nothing but the thoughts of it. But as Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition only had made her reſolve th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> undertaking it, and that before ſhe had engaged her ſelf, ſhe had neither conſulted her Heart no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her Love, they made her know when ſhe the leaſt thought of it. That they ought to be of the Party and that nothing is well done with out them. Having thus taken al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the meaſures that were requiſite fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her journy, ſhe quitted <hi>Paris,</hi> to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Havre,</hi> where a Ship attended her. Her abſence rendred me the moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> unfortunate of all Lovers, cauſing in me an extreme grief, and in my diſpair <hi>I</hi> made Complaints capable of moveing a heart of Marble. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> at length having ſpent many ſighs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150241:32"/>took Poſt and went to expect her <hi>Havre,</hi> with deſign to uſe in that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ace the utmoſt efforts for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wading her from that Voyage. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>archioneſs arriving after five days <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rny, was much furprized to find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there in a diſguiſed habit. Her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove was renewed in ſeeing me, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> felt in her heart a motion of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erneſs which made her blame her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bition: As <hi>I</hi> perceived ſomething <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f it, <hi>I</hi> made uſe of that good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent; for after having given her a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppoſed Letter, which ſerved me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a pretence, having obliged her to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſee the Cittadel, which is one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fineſt and ſtrongeſt in <hi>Europe,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> walked upon the Baſtions, at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> foot of which the Waves of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> beat, <hi>I</hi> took an Occaſion to ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> her of the infidelity of that Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ent: and ſome wrecks of a Veſſel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had been caſt away a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e in the Road, preſenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elves in that moment to our view,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150241:33"/>it ſo luckily ſeconded my Deſign, that fear and love procured in the mind of the Marchioneſs the effect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had promiſed my ſelf. She chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Reſolution ſhe had taken of quitting me. We renewed our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Proteſtations, of never parting, and for the better covering this change with a ſpecious pretence the Marchioneſs feigned to be very ill; and it was reſolved that <hi>I</hi> ſhould not appear till after the Veſſel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> put to Sea; Whereupon ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> carried immediately to her Lodging, where, as ſoon as ſhe came ſhe di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not fail to go to Bed, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain as may be imagined. The ableſt Phyſitian was ſent for to her, and <hi>I</hi> had ſo well inſtructed him, that he needed no more to perſwade all the world that ſhe was very fick, and that every one beleived her life in danger: Inſomuch that the Captain of the ſhip, after having waited fifteen days in vain for her
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150241:33"/>recovery, was conſtrained to make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for <hi>Poland.</hi> Having noting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ore to deſire, <hi>I</hi> made known <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Marchioneſs that for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>king away all ſuſpicion, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had contributed to her ſtay, it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>as requiſite <hi>I</hi> ſhould return as <hi>I</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame, to which ſhe conſented; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> days after ſhe alſo arriving at <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> ſhe ſo well perſwaded the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dy, who had engaged her, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ief ſhe had to have fallen ſick, and at having been able to take the oyage, that ſhe diſcovered no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ctation, and ever preſerved for her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all her eſteem and affection: Both of us well ſatisfied with one another, we paſſed very ſweetly ſix months together: But in ſine Love having reſolved to part us, renewed the Occaſion of going into <hi>Poland</hi> at a time <hi>I</hi> leaſt dreamt of it; for the Queen impatiently expecting a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verneſs, and not ſeeing her arrive in the Veſſel that was to have brought
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150241:34"/>her, fancying her Orders were neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, addreſſed her ſelf to another Lady to ſend her One, which the Marchioneſs having notice of, ſhe ſo employed her intereſt with the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Lady who had engaged her, that by her means ſhe was again deſtined for that employ, having a real deſign of going. All that I could do to perſwade her from this fancy was of no effect; and the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs apprehending a ſecond ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, obliged me not to leave <hi>Paris.</hi> Wherefore <hi>I</hi> was conſtrained to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to it, and to content my ſelf with the aſſurance ſhe gave of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver forgetting me. My tears and ſighs had no Power, and the time ſhe had demanded to ſettle her affairs being expired, ſhe went aboard the Veſſel which was to carry her, and arrived ſafely at the Court of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> where ſhe was received by their Majeſties with all the kindneſs ſhe could have hoped. Of all the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150241:34"/>diſpleaſures that Love cauſes in us, abfence is certainly the moſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; There are its true ſeveral O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whoſe ſtings are very piercing, but when we are far from what we love, nothing certainly lies heavier upon us: Wherefore it is eaſie to imagine what my trouble was. As <hi>I</hi> loved the Marchionels tenderly, I looked upon that ſeparation as a kind of Death; and that Thought made ſuch an impreſſion upon my mind, that in a few days <hi>I</hi> appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo changed, that my friends were all ſurprized at it. <hi>I</hi> was no longer ſeen in that gay humour which <hi>I</hi> had before, and tho <hi>I</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to conceal my melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and recover my mirth, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared a certain languiſhing in all my actions, which made known that my ſoul was far from me. As much as <hi>Paris</hi> had been dear to me, <hi>I</hi> as much abhorred it ſince the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs had left it, and in the middle
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150241:35"/>of that great City <hi>I</hi> lived as if <hi>I</hi> had been in a Wilderneſs. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance alone of my Miſtreſs poſſeſſed all my thoughts, and not being able to live any longer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing her, <hi>I</hi> took the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of following her. But ſuch a voyage beeing very long, <hi>I</hi> was wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to take ſuch precautions with my Father as that it might not afflict him: <hi>I</hi> went to ſee him, and ſtayed four or five months at his houſe, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring which time having made known to the Marchioneſs the deſign <hi>I</hi> had of going to her, ſhe took meaſures with the Queen of <hi>Poland,</hi> and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that <hi>I</hi> was her Relation, ſhe made her Majeſty think fit <hi>I</hi> ſhould make a voyage to her Court. She had even the goodneſs to declare to her that <hi>I</hi> might not be uſeleſs there, and that ſhe would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let her ſee that ſhe took part in all that concerned her. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs being thus aſſured that <hi>I</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:150241:35"/>ſhould be well received, gave me notice of it by this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Marchioneſs des <hi>Roches,</hi> to the Baron de <hi>Saint-Cir.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT is very difficult to have ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations as you, my dear Coſin, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſionately deſiring to ſee them, principally in a Country where I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not put Confidence in many people: Wherefore if you ſtill perſevere in the deſign of travelling, you will never meet with more pleaſure than in</hi> Poland, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I ſhall receive you there with all the joy imaginable, and that the King and Queen have had the goodneſs to declare they ſhould graciouſly conſider you. As the Court is all French, you will find no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it that is ſavage, except the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits, and I hope when you are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with it, you will find it as diverting as that of</hi> France. <hi>But tho theſe Conſiderations are very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, I will however believe, that they are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:150241:36"/>leſs inviting than the deſire you have of ſeeing a Relation who loves you tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and who ſhould eſteem her ſelf very happy, if ſhe might once more aſſure you by word of mouth that ſhe will as long as ſhe lives be entirely Yours</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Marchioneſs des <hi>Roches.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>As <hi>I</hi> expected with the uſual im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience of paſſionate Lovers News from the Marchioneſs, <hi>I</hi> received this Letter with all the tenderneſs <hi>I</hi> was capable of: I kiſſed it a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand times, and read it over as often: Inſomuch that only thinking of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſee her, I in ſome meaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered my briskneſs; and after having cauſed my Father to conſent to my abſence, I made a very mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Equipage, and went to <hi>Havre</hi> with deſign to go on board there the firſt: Veſſel I ſhould find: But not being willing to ſurprize the Marchioneſs, I acquainted her with it in theſe terms.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:150241:36"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Baron de <hi>Saint-Cir</hi> to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs des <hi>Roches.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOu never made a more equitable judgement than that of believing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y dear Coſin, that you alone could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>blige me to go into Poland: Not but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat I have an extream acknowledgment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f the kindneſs their Majeſties have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ared they ſhould have for me, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat it might agreably flatter the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition of a young Gentleman. But the tyes of Blood, and a certain I know not what, which I find I have for you more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>han for all the reſt of the world, makes much more impreſſion upon my mind: and when I think I ſhall again ſee the moſt lovely relation in the world, and that ſhe her ſelf will be delighted with it, my ſoul is filled with an unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible joy, and I complain of all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oments that I employ for the preparing my Equipage, Wherefore you may judge if I ſhall neglect to embark in the firſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:150241:37"/>Veſſel that goes from this Port, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther having likewiſe given me leave t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> travel; and if the Winds would hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> my vows, I ſhould certainly have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> honour of ſeeing you ſuddainly, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> making appear to you the acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I have of your Cares, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> happineſs you are willing to procure m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Baron de <hi>Saint-Cir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>After having ſent this Letter to the Poſt, I waited at <hi>Havre</hi> more than a month for the conveniency of a Veſſel, which was come to take in Marchandice for <hi>Poland,</hi> my im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patience may be better imagined than I can expreſs it, and in all my life I never found the days ſo long I went every moment to the Port to ſee if the Ship could depart, and when I found the wind fair I was mad we were not to make uſe of it; But Sea-men are a people without Reaſon, as well as without Love, wherefore I could not oblige them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150241:37"/>to put to Sea before the time they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad projected, what prayers ſoever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> made them. Being thus conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to wait, I took the reſolution of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eing a pretty woman, and of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt Quality of the City, I had known her at <hi>Paris,</hi> and if I be not deceived ſhe had ſome kind of eſteem for me. She received me with all the teſtimonies of kindneſs and ioy I could have hoped for; and if I had been capable of reliſhing the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſments of the ſeaſon, I ſhould not have been weary with her; but all that lovely perſon could do, it was impoſſible for her to ſee me one day without melancholy. In fine the time beeing arrived I expected with ſo much impatience, that Lady would needs accompany me on Board, where after having wiſhed me all manner of happineſs, ſhe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly embracing me bid me farewel. The Son that had not appeared in more than a week, ſhewed by his
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150241:38"/>return the part he took in my good fortune, and it ſeemed according to all appearances, that I was to make a happy voyage. But we were hardly twenty Leagues at Sea, than the great agitation of the ſhip made me ſo ſick, that in two or three days I loſt my ſpeech, and could not make my ſelf underſtood otherwiſe than by ſigns. During my ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in this manner, there aroſe on a ſuddain ſo furious a tempeſt, that the ſea-men not being able to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern their ſhip, were conſtrained to tear down the ſails, and to abandon it to the mercy of that Element. Death preſented it ſelf on all ſides, and the moſt daring apprehended to find there their Grave; inſomuch that I had been extreamly happy in my diſeaſe, if the Maſter of the ſhip, who was a man naturally barbarous enough, and of thoſe ſort of people who are given to ſuperſtition, had not fancied that I was the cauſe of
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:150241:38"/>this change, becauſe he had ſeen that Lady embrace me upon the Deck when ſhe bid me Adieu. Wherefore notwithſtanding all the reſiſtance of his people he would needs caſt me into the Sea, ſaying that the tempeſt would certainly ceaſe, and that they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. In this cruel deſign aſſiſted with ſome of his ſea-men, he took me and carried me upon the Deck, and they had already half put me into the Sea, when that a Religious touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Compaſſion, couragiouſly oppoſed his Barbarouſneſs, and held me by a foot; But as the Maſter per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevered to drown me, tho he remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to him, that being a perſon of Quality my death might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged and coſt him his head. At length ſeeing that his reaſons were not heard, and wiſely conſidering that to oppoſe was the means of rendring his Charity uſeleſs, he found this expedient, that if I did not ſpeak
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150241:39"/>the next day, and that I were ſtill ſick, he conſented they ſhould caſt me into the Sea, to which the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter agreed and I was left upon the Deck, without my ſervants daring to take care of me. Not having loſt my hearing, and underſtanding very well all that was ſaid, it is eaſie to imagine with what a fright I was ſeized. The certain death I ſaw preſented it ſelf to my imagination with all the horrours which accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany it, and I thought of nothing but preparing my ſelf for it, when that Heaven made a miracle in my ſavour, for the air clearing up about three a clock in the morning, there fell a little ſhower, which having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked me out of the trance I was, I crept as well as I could to ſome tackling, and having ſuckt with my tongue the water which dropt down, it ſo well moiſtned my throat, that it took away the ſharpneſs which hindred me from ſpeaking: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150241:39"/>that with the day light I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered my ſpeech, and the Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo become calm, the Maſter ſurprized with theſe alterations, not only left off perſevering in the baſe deſign he had; But having told him I went to the Court of <hi>Poland</hi> by the Kings Order, (which put him in a terrible fright being his Subject) He took ſo much care of me, that ſome days after I recovered my perfect health, and had ſo abſolute a power over the Ship, that I diſpoſed of it as if it had been mine. Wherefore we thought of nothing but of making uſe of the fair wind we had, when that being ready to enter the <hi>Baltique</hi> ſea, having taken his Glaſs upon the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice they ſaw a ſail, he diſcovered that that ſhip endeavoured to get the wind of him, and that it was an Engliſh Man of War; as he appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended with reaſon he ſhould be inſulted, he did all he could to avoid their coming up to him, but after
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:150241:40"/>having uſed all his efforts one whole day to prevent being taken, the man of war in the evening coming within Canon-ſhot, made three ſhots upon our Veſſel, which made the Maſter reſolve to caſt Anchor to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him. I did what I could to oblige thoſe who travelled with me, to put our ſelves in a poſture of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but notwithſtanding my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances and the deſire I had of fighting we were taken by thoſe Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates, who entring our ſhip, ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified them that were in it, that two of the ſix Hoſpital Maids that the Queen of <hi>Poland</hi> cauſed to come from <hi>France</hi> to eſtabliſh them in her Kingdom, caſt themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea where they were drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they ſtript all the others and took from them what they had of value, and diſcovering by my cloaths that I was no common perſon, and that they might have a good ranſom from me, they made me only lay down
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150241:40"/>my Arms, and treating me with more Civility than I could have hoped, we were carried to <hi>London; Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> the Uſurper of the Kingdom reigned there at that time under the name of Protector. The Maſter of the ſhip remonſtrated to him that he had been in <hi>France</hi> by order of the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that all that was taken belonged to him, he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Paſſports and demanded his liberty; but it would not be granted him, and we were conſtrained to wait above a month, for news from the Court of <hi>Poland.</hi> The King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſurprized to hear what had hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to us, ſent an expreſs to the Protector, to whom having confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what the Maſter had advanced, the Protector ordered that all ſhould be reſtored that had been taken from us, which was punctually executed, inſomuch that putting again to Sea after incredible fatigues, we arrived at length at <hi>Danzick,</hi> from whence
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150241:41"/>thinking to have gone to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> I was much ſurprized when they told me that the ſickneſs had drove the Courtaway, which was wandring from City to City, for the avoiding that Cruel diſeaſe which depopulated all the Kingdom. But having learnt that it ſtopped at <hi>Lublin</hi> where it would ſtay ſometime; I ſent one of my ſervants to the Marchioneſs to give her notice of my arrival, and to know where I might ſee her. But when he arrived at <hi>Lublin,</hi> the King was already gone from thence for the <hi>Dutchy</hi> of <hi>Lithuania;</hi> He joyned the Court at <hi>Vilna,</hi> and delivered my Letter to the Marchioneſs, who having as much impatience to ſee me, as I had of making known to her, that ſhe alone ſtill made all my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, that nothing might hinder me from making all the expedition poſſible, ſhe ſent me back my man with one of hers, who knew the language and the wayes. In effect
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150241:41"/>they had no ſooner delivered to me the Letter the Marchioneſs wrote to me, than that I begun my journy for <hi>Vilna.</hi> My impatience made me make a thouſand uſeleſs vows, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expreſs to you the greatneſs of my trouble: But in fine I arrived at the place where I deſired to be with ſo much paſſion. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs whoſe abſence had not at all diminiſhed her affections receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me with much joy, and as ſhe found in me alſo the ſame ſentiments I had ever had for her, Our firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview produced the uſual effect of extream paſſions. We were a long time without being able to ſpeak; and after having acquainted one another with what had happned to us ſince our parting, I had the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of receiving from her in that occaſion, all the moſt obliging marks of eſteem and kindneſs that I could have expected. Two days after the Marchioneſs having preſented me to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150241:42"/>their Majeſties, who beleived me her near Relation, I was received by them with ſo much goodneſs, that I ſhall preſerve the memory of it as long as I live. All the Court did me likewiſe more honour and civility than I could have expected; and eſpecially you, my Lord, treated me after ſo obliging a manner, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the man of the world, the fulleſt of acknowledgment, I vow to you that from that day, I have ever had a very great paſſion of ſerving you, and of being of the number of your friends. <hi>Ragieski</hi> who had very peaceably liſtened to the Baron, having interrupted him to anſwer his Civility, and to make him new Proteſtations of frienſhip, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his diſcourſe thus. As I had no other ambition than that of lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Marchioneſs and of being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, the liberty I had of ſeeing and ſpeaking every time I could wiſh it with Civility, rendered me
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150241:42"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e moſt happy of all Lovers. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing gave me Employs, as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow, wherein I have endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to anſwer the good opinion he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of all thoſe of our Nation. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>archioneſs continued to love me, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ove her with the ſame tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs as I did the firſt day; and it is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich makes me ſomething melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oly, notwithſtanding the good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear; and the other pleaſures I receive in your Houſe. This is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y Lord, all of conſideration that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ean acquaint you with; and as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou are the only One I have intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with my ſecret, I hope it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>in ſo with you; ſince you ſee it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of conſiderable conſequence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat you take part in all that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erns me. The Baron having left off ſpeaking, <hi>Ragieski</hi> neglected nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat might confirm him in the good opinion he had of him. And after having applauded his Conſtancy and his Choice; Supper time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:150241:43"/>they went to the Vice-Chancellor's Ladyes apartment, whoſe Letter the King received with ſo tender and paſſionate tranſports, that after having read it ſeveral times, it ſeemed as if he could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver part from it; he was no longer ſeen in that gloomy humour he was in before. All people were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized at it; and taſting already by advance the pleaſure that was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him, his joy was read in his face, waiting however with impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the day of Rendevouz. He gave orders for hunting exactly half way from the Vice-Chancellor's houſe, and as the days were ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhort, he departed in the morning, and in the heat of the Chace, ſtealing from the croud of Courtiers, he was not long before he came to the place, where the Vice-Chancellors Lady as impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as himſelf, expected him, the King being only followed by one Officer
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150241:43"/>in whom he put great confidence. It was a Country houſe in the middle of the Foreſt, and far enough from the high ways. Being the dwelling place of a Nobleman meanly rich, who was not at all ſurprized to ſee hunters there. But as a pretence was requiſite for ſtaying, the Vice-Chancellor's Lady being only fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by her faithful Governeſs and the Baron's Gentleman of the horſe who knew the ways, had had the precaution to ſay at her arrival, that ſhe had fallen from her horſe and was ſomething hurt. The Nobleman had left his houſe to her that ſhe might take reſt, and went to ſee his labourers work. Thus the King finding no obſtacle to his contentment, had ſo agreable an entertainment with the Vice-Chancellor's Lady, that nothing could be added to the pleaſure they had together: They recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced themſelves with Uſury for
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150241:44"/>the time they had loſt; and while that all thoſe that had followed <hi>Caſimer</hi> to the chaſe, were in extreme pain of finding him, as well as <hi>Ragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eski</hi> was on his part for his Lady, whom he beleived loſt, becauſe ſhe was not at the death of the Stag. They paſſed their time ſweetly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether. They were two hours in that manner, and in that time a great many things are ſaid when we are as much in love as they were. But the Governeſs fearing a ſurprize, and thinking the time long, came and told them they ought to think of retreating: Inſomuch that they muſt part, but it was not without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme pain they did ſo, and that each of them went their way. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy was not long before ſhe joyned her Company who were in ſearch of her; ſhe told them ſhe had loſt her ſelf in the wood, they eaſily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived her, and as ſhe was very well ſatisfied, and that they were
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150241:44"/>ſo likewiſe with the good ſucceſs of their hunting; they all returned with much joy to <hi>Ragieski</hi>'s Caſtle. The reſt of the day paſſed very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greably; the Vice-Chancellor's La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy acquainted the Baron in few words with the ſucceſs of the Rende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouz. <hi>Caſimer</hi> not being obliged to give an account of his actions, had an overplus of pleaſure to ſee at his arrival at <hi>Warſaw,</hi> how earneſt they were to know what had been become of him: and the Baron re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning the day after to Court, after having been well regaled at <hi>Ragies<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ki</hi>'s houſe, who was charmed with his Wit and his other Qualities: They would have all had reaſon to have been well contented, if the Marchioneſs, knowing nothing of what paſſed, had not taken ombrage of the Baron's viſit: But as ſhe was naturally jealous, and that the Vice-Chancellor's Lady was pretty and young, ſhe could not hold from
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150241:45"/>reproaching him with the long ſtay he had made in her houſe, and making likewiſe reflection of his earneſtneſs to ſpeak to her when ſhe was at Court, there needed nothing more to perſwade her of his being in love with her: Inſomuch that in the firſt tranſport of her jealouſy, ſhe ſpoke ſuch ſharp and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous things to the Baron, that he ſeemed to be the moſt treacherous of all men. I do not at all wonder, ſaid ſhe to him in anger, that for ſome months you have not had that application for me that cauſed all my joy, my kindneſs too well aſſured you of my heart, that you ſhould ſtill make it your delight and your pleaſure, you love—There ſhe could not proceed, nor detain her tears; but a moment after recovering her ſpeach, yes you are unfaithful; and do not think I am ignorant you have been at <hi>Ragieski</hi>'s to give your new Miſtris a heart that belongs to me,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150241:45"/>and of whom I ſhall revenge my ſelf. The Baron being extremely aſtoniſhed at theſe threatnings did all that he could to undeceive the Marchioneſs of the errour ſhe was in; he caſt himſelf at her knees, which he very tenderly embraced, he ſigh'd, he wept, he ſwore a thouſand times that he ſtill loved her with the ſame ſidelity, and that his paſſion ſhould be eternal. But tho he told the truth, all this did not cure the fair diſpleaſed One; the Vice-Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor's Lady made her affraid; and tho he was perſwaded it was dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous for him to diſcover the Kings ſecret, he choſe rather to riſque all events, than to ſee her any longer diſpleaſed with him. True Lovers cannot conceal any thing from their Miſtreſſes, he knew ſhe only treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him ill becauſe ſhe would not loſe him; wherefore he acquainted her with what we have ſaid of the Kings Amours with the Vice-Chancellor's
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150241:46"/>Lady; this ſetled her mind, and the Baron and the Marchioneſs were ſo well reconciled, that he did not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſhe would impart to other people the ſecret he truſted her with.</p>
            <p>While that all this paſſed in this manner, his affairs of War were not in ſo good a poſture. The Diet aſſembled at <hi>Warſaw;</hi> where the Vice-Chancellor was obliged to be and to bring his wife, who could ſtay no longer in the Country by reaſon of the ſeaſon. The Nobles appeared there allarmed, and in ſtrange diviſions: The Eccleſiaſticks complained highly that their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges were violated, and that the King had conſented in favour of the <hi>Coſaques</hi> to the rupture of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made between the Roman and Greek Church, and that every one might live according to his beleif: and both the one and the other in ſtead of Uniting to hinder the ruin
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150241:46"/>of the Republick, conſumed the time in particular diſputes, and that great Aſſembly was hardly able to take the neceſſary Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the approaching Campagne. It would be a kind of Miracle if a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing could long entertain an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous intrigue without diſcovery. Kings are ſo uſed to be abſolute in their Wills, that they cannot always conſtrain themſelves. <hi>Caſimer</hi> took ſo much pleaſure in entertaining the Vice-Chancellor's Lady every time ſhe came to the Palace, that tho he ſaw her elſe where more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently, he could not hold from ſpeaking to her. It was perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was talked of, ſhe was pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; all the world knew that Love was the Kings ruling paſſion, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one likewiſe beleived that the Vice-Chancellor's Lady poſſeſſed his favours; <hi>Ragieski</hi> took notice of it as well as the others, but the honour <hi>Caſimer</hi> did him, not being
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150241:47"/>for his convenience, he made known ſomething of it to his wife who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the King thereof. They were for ſometime more reſerved, which augmented his cares and jealouſy, and as the Lady was not cautious enough in concealing her paſſion, in the end her love betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her. <hi>Ragieski</hi> unluckily found one day her little Cabinet open, ſhe kept the Kings Letters in it, as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious marks of his defeat and of the power of her eys, he took them and was in diſpair to ſee what he was very unwilling to have found. In the firſt tranſport of his fury, he more than once deliberated to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice her to his Diſpair; but as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful as ſhe appeared to him, he loved her too well to loſe her; he contented himſelf with outraging her by terrible words, and to ſhut her up in a Chamber of which he took the key: This was not yet enough or a man ſo irritated as <hi>Ragieski,</hi> he
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150241:47"/>knew the Queen could not patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer the amorous thefts of <hi>Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> he went to her immediately, and dilivered into her hands the Letters he had found: The Queen ſeemed no leſs outraged than himſelf, and as ſhe had more than one reaſon, that obliged her to wiſh <hi>Caſimer</hi> might not be won from her, ſhe promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Ragieski</hi> to hinder the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their diſhonour: She was a Woman of her word, neither did ſhe fail to ſhew her Reſentment to the King, and he ſo impatiently ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Queens Reproaches, that it did but augment his paſſion for the Vice-Chancellor's Lady, and <hi>Ragieski</hi> well knowing to what dangers one is expoſed, when in diſgrace with his Prince, reſolved to ſeek his ſafety in his retreat; Wherefore he returned to his houſe, whither he carried his wife, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that time which allays the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ills, would appeaſe the Kings an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150241:48"/>and extinguiſh his flames. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it happned quite contrary, for the King who found in the airy Converſation of the Vice-Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor's Lady, Charms which eaſed his mind of thoſe troubleſome fatigues from which Monarchs are no more exempted than other men, and who ſtill hoped for greater favours, find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf on a ſuddain deprived of the pleaſures ſhe gave him, ſent an Order to <hi>Ragieski</hi> to return to Court to render his Majeſty the ſervice he was obliged to by his Charge. All Courts are full of ſuch people as inſult over the unfortunate, and that to get by their diſgrace, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge themſelves, ever find out con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed Crimes. In a ſhort time <hi>Ragieski</hi> was accuſed of caballing againſt the intereſts of the State, and was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed of ſome ſecret Intelligences with the Enemies of the Crown: Inſomuch that the Senators and Nuncios of the Kingdom depoſed
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150241:48"/>him from his Charge, baniſhed him for ever, and confiſcated his goods: All the efforts of the Arch-Biſhop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Gneſne</hi> Primate of the Kingdom, could not prevent this Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>olt, and the unfortunate <hi>Ragieski</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as conſtrained to go ſeek refuge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forreign Contries. But as he had many conſiderable Relations, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he was a man of wit, he ſo well knew how to diſcover to the <hi>Swedes</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he weakneſs of the Republick, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the end he rendered his vengeance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tal to <hi>Caſimer,</hi> as we ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſee. Thus the King having no more obſtacle in his love, and the Queen not being able to hinder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s being entirely the Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ellor's Ladyes; he cauſed her to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome to Court under pretence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ringing up there an Only Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſhe had had by <hi>Ragieski,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aving given her all the confiſcated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ands and goods of her Husband, he continued the ſeeing and loving her
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:150241:49"/>with yet more tenderneſs and paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than he had done before. He triumphed over the Queen and <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gieski</hi> for ſome months, not keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any meaſures for the conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Love he had for the Vice-Chancellor's wife, whom he pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly ſaw as often as he pleaſed. Some of <hi>Ragieski</hi>'s Relations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to murmur very highly, and the Vice-Chancellor who was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to <hi>Stockholm</hi> to the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> ſo well inflamed them by the correſpondences he held with them, that having made them comprehend that the honour of all the Nobility was branded in his perſon. As the Nation is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally jealous as well as haughty, at the length all the Nobles ſo publickly complained of <hi>Caſimer</hi>'s proceedure, that tho nothing was Criminal that had paſſed between him and the Vice-Chancellor's Lady, he was conſtrained to yeild to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:150241:49"/>reaſons of State and to abandon her. To expreſs here the greatneſs of his and the Ladys grief, is what cannot be done by words. Tho a King and highly ſenſible of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ury that was done him, he was forced however to ſuffer it, and to ſtifle his love and his anger: Tho <hi>Ragieski</hi>'s ought to have been leſſened by this kind of victory which he gained at his turn, and that he ought to have ſpared his Country; yet the particular hatred he had conceived againſt the King overcoming all other conſiderations, he made uſe of this way for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfying his Revenge. All the world knows that <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Suder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannia</hi> being become King of <hi>Sweden</hi> by the Revolt of the Biſhops and the people, who had embraced the Doctrine of Doctor <hi>Diſteben,</hi> he maintained himſelf there againſt his Nephew <hi>Sigismund</hi> Father of <hi>Caſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> who had been elected King of
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150241:50"/>
               <hi>Poland,</hi> and to whom the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi> belonged by right of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus</hi> that famous Conqueror likewiſe main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining himſelf therein, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the efforts of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus;</hi> after ſeveral bloody Wars, they made a Truce, during which they were to labour for a good Peace. But theſe two Kings being dead, <hi>Caſimer</hi> renewed this Truce with <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> the only Daughter of <hi>Guſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avus;</hi> who having reſigned the Crown in favour of <hi>Charles</hi> her Coſin German; <hi>Caſimer</hi> who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that this abdication could not be made to his Prejudice; the Crown of <hi>Sweden</hi> Legitimately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to him, ſent a Gentleman to the States of <hi>Sweden</hi> aſſembled for the Coronation of <hi>Charles,</hi> that he might form an oppoſition on his part: But this oppoſition not being conſidered, and <hi>Charles</hi> touched to the quick with this proceedure: <hi>Ragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eski</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:150241:50"/>ſeeing the Occaſion favourable for the puſhing on his reſentment, employed all the talents of his wit for the animating <hi>Charles</hi> to reſent the affront that <hi>Caſimer</hi> had newly done him, and adding to that the great Correſpondencies he enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with the principal Lords of the Kingdom, who could no longer ſuffer his Government, he gave him ſo certain hopes that he might be elected in his place, that at length <hi>Charles</hi> reſolved to break the Truce, and to make War upon <hi>Poland.</hi> In the mean time there were Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors at <hi>Lubec</hi> who laboured for the Peace; <hi>Caſimer</hi> ſeeing the Nobility alienated, his Authority leſſened, a thouſand Contradictions in the Aſſemblies, <hi>Lithuania</hi> in the power of the Moſcovites, and the <hi>Coſaques</hi> revolted; all this obliged him to deſire it, and to yeild up ſeveral points which he would not have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned in another juncture. But
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150241:51"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> animated by <hi>Ragieski</hi> chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Policy in changing Deſign. His Miniſters ſought out new difficulties, and tho <hi>Caſimer</hi> had renounced in favour of <hi>Charles</hi> all the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he had upon the Kingdom of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and had even conſented the three Crowns he bore in his arms ſhould be taken away, which was the only ſubject that had obliged <hi>Sigiſmond</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſtaus</hi> to make War. The <hi>Swedes</hi> paſſed to other demands, that under pretence of ſtill labouring on the Peace, they might make their preparations, fool the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and diſpoſſeſs him without his being able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend himſelf. <hi>Charles</hi> cauſed like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be publiſhed his pretenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Dutchy of <hi>Cleves</hi> and <hi>Juliers,</hi> for the better concealing his Deſigns. And as the truce ought to have laſted ſix years longer, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimer</hi> could not imagine that <hi>Charles</hi> would break it, and therefore took
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150241:51"/>no precautions. He thought at that time of curing the Melancholy the forced retreat of the Vice-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ellor's Lady had caſt him into, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eart could not live without loving, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was his natural inclination: he had formerly caſt his Eyes upon one of the Queens Maids of Honour, He daily ſaw her without going out of the Palace: ſhe was no Poland<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, ſhe was younger than the Vice-Chancellor's wife, and was not leſs fair. <hi>Caſimer</hi> fancied he could not do better than to love her, and endeavour the being beloved: The greateſt obſtacle he found in it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the great ſeverity with which the Marchioneſs lived with her Maids of Honour, obſerving the leaſt of their actions. That La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy being affectionately beloved by the Queen, appeared likewiſe ſo fixed in her intereſts, that the King was not a little perplexed. But the faithful Baron was a great help to
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150241:52"/>him, for having diſcovered to him his new paſſion, as he was much in the Marchioneſſes favour, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed him to employ the credit he had with her, for the obliging her to furniſh the King with the means of ſeeing his Miſtres in ſecret. The Baron intereſſed himſelf too much in all that might pleaſe <hi>Caſimer,</hi> to omitt any thing for the engaging the Marchioneſs to ſerve him. He knew her Delicacy, and was not ignorant that the propoſition he was to make her, would furiouſly diſpleaſe her; But he reſolved to ſuffer all for the contenting his Maſter. She for whom the King ſighed was called <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfeild,</hi> ſhe was a German, and but eighteen years old; Her ſhape was fine, and of thoſe that may be called advantagious, her face oval, her Eyes blew, well turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in which there was ſeen a certain languiſhing mixed with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150241:52"/>vacity, ſo great a proportion in all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perſon, that one more beautiful could hardly be found. But with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe advantages ſhe had ſo quick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it and ſo juſt a diſcernment, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is not to be wondered if <hi>Caſimer</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd in her wherewith to comfort in for the loſs he had. As the noiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his firſt paſſion had ruined <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and that the Queen continually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atched the leaſt of his actions; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s love diſguiſed it ſelf a long time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>der the name of good will; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Eyes alone made known to <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> that he had in is heart ſomething more for her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an that general eſteem One has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or all fair Perſons. The King loſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o occaſion of ſpeaking to her, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen he did it, it was in ſo obliging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erms, that it might be eaſirly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ined his was not indifferent. The Marchioneſs perceived it, which made her the more ſtrictly obſerve the Conduct of <hi>Mademoiſellede Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field;</hi>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:150241:53"/>ſhe alſo ſpoke of it one day to the Baron, and declared to him that this paſſion of the King ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely perplexed her. The Baron made uſe of the occaſion to qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> himſelf of what he had promiſed <hi>Caſimer,</hi> and looking upon the Marchioneſs with a paſſionate air. I am ſo uſed, Madam, ſaid he to her, to ask you favours, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive: marks of your goodneſs, that I know not if you will have tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of diſengaging me from the word I have given to the King, that you ſhall not traverſe the paſſion h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> has for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Scanfield</hi> I very well know that what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> demand of you is extraordinary that it is in a manner affronting you to pretend it. But likewiſe Madam, added he, the more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence you ſhall uſe upon your ſelf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the more ſhall I be indebted to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> There are Kings like Torrents who deſtroy all that oppoſes their
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:150241:53"/>paſſage: You know what it coſt <hi>Pagieski,</hi> and alſo the little ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction the Queen had in ſhewing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er jealouſy. The King's love is ſo violent that it cannot ſuffer any engmentation; He is liberal and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>akes care of raiſing me, but this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not what moſt engages me; He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onours me with his Confidence; he diſcovers to me the moſt ſecret, thoughts of his heart. In fine, Madam, I judge of the pleaſune you ſhall do him by that I ſhould receive, if the like ſervice was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>endred me in regard of you. The Marchioneſs who had hearkened to all this diſcourſe with much at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, was very much perplexed now to anſwer it; ſhe clearly ſaw that all the Baron told her merited reflection to be made upon it. But what ſhe owed the Queen and what ſhe owed her ſelf at that time overcame all theſe conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſhe was ſo diſpleaſed with
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:150241:54"/>the Baron, that he was conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to come to ſubmiſſions for the appeaſing her exaſperated mind. However he did not deſpair of bringing her to the point he deſired; and having acquainted the King with what he had done, this diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d but augment his ardour, inſomuch that he was upon the point of declaring himſelf openly. In that thought the amourous Prince made a thouſand different Projects, but coming to conſider the impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that this would make upon the Queens Spirit, who would uſe all manner of means for the ruining his hopes; he conjured the Baron to make a ſecond effort with the Marchioneſs, for the conquering her ſcruples, for the ſuceeding in it; the Baron redoubled his cares and applications, he never quitted the Marchioneſs; and as nothing is impoſſible to Love when it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns it ſelf, the Baron's tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:150241:54"/>ſo touched the Marchioneſs, that at length ſhe reſolved to be of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he intelligence. <hi>Caſimer</hi> had an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>expreſſible joy; he made magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent preſents to the Marchioneſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd promiſing himſelf the enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of thouſands of pleaſures, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e means was to be ſought for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking him ſee his Miſtreſs with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fety. The Marchioneſſes apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was judged the moſt conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent and the leaſt ſuſpected; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he difficulty was to come ſecretly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere. The other maids of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ours Chambers were to be paſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and to win two Guards who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er kept ſentinel in the Gallery, which appeared an invincible ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>acle, becauſe theſe Guards were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aily changed: Wherefore they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hoſe the moſt dangerous means <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut likewiſe the moſt certain, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as to paſs thro a window which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oked into the Court, thro which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Baron took the King with a
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:150241:55"/>Ladder into the Marchioneſſes Chamber: there is nothing to which we expoſe not our ſelves when we are in Love. <hi>Caſimer</hi> approved this expedient, tho dangerous for his perſon; and all being diſpoſed in that manner, the Marchioneſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to careſs <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> more than uſual, ſhe made her the Conſident of her ſecrets, that ſhe might have part in hers, and rallying her agreeably upon the Complaiſancies the King had for her; in a little time ſhe won her good Opinion, and diſcovered to her all he was reſolved to do for the giving her marks of his Love. As <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield</hi> was haughty, ſhe received very coldly the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Marchioneſs made her, which rendred her very uneaſie; but in fine the pleaſure of being belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a King, whoſe tenderneſs was known, too agreeably flattered her imagination to deſpiſe the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:150241:55"/>Conqueſt. She conſented to the Rendevouz the Marchioneſs had appointed her; and the hour ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed being come, the Baron <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt out a Ladder to the King with which he mounted into her apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. There it was that this Prince found that Love treats Kings as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men; all his greatneſs quitted him as well as his Courage. <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oiſelle de Schanfield</hi> appeared to him the moſt formidable perſon in the world, tho ſhe was there more ſoft, yet he durſt hardly offer her his heart. Neither is there any thing which more perplexes a Lover than to ſay he loves: all his actions pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh his Love, and he very well contented; but when words are to be found to explain them, a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Confuſion mingled with fear ſo ſeiſes on all his Spirits, that he cannot diſcover what he even dyes thorowly to perſwade. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the diſorder the King was in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:150241:56"/>was not uſeleſs to him; and tho he had told <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> all he had reſolved to ſay to her, perhaps it would not have made the ſame impreſſion upon her mind as his ſilence and his ſighs. It is the uſual effect of great paſſions to be ever mute, Nothing touches more a fair perſon than to ſee greatneſs humbled at her feet, a King ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant to Charms that are very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and in truth it was all theſe conſiderations that made <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Schanfield</hi> loſe a part of her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural haughtineſs in that Occaſion; ſhe felt in her heart unuſual moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and if her baſhfulneſs hindred her from declaring to the King that his paſſion did not diſpleaſe her; it is certain that ſhe conceived a great eſteem for him, and that ſhe ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intereſſed her ſelf. But the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of conquering a young heart which had never been touched be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned to his Love, it may be
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:150241:56"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid that that uncertainty was not without delight; One loves natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to ſurmount all that makes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, and the hope there is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anquiſhing and recompenſing our ſelves, cauſes ſometimes more joy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han favours would do. But all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ings hopes had like to have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uined by an accident which put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s perſon in extreme danger. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as ever been obſerved at the Court <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f <hi>Poland</hi> the Cuſtom of ſetting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wo Guards before the apartment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the maids of Honour, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay know what paſſes there. One <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay that the Baron <hi>de Saint Cir</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould not go to the Marchioneſſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>partment, by reaſon of an indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which obliged him to keep <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is bed; the King not being able <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o paſs the window as he uſed to do, would needs go thro the maids of Honours Gallery: But after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed the firſt Sentinel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut being perceived, becauſe it
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:150241:57"/>was late and that, the Souldier was without doubt aſleep; when he was upon the point of entring the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, the other Souldier ſtopped him by a who goes there? to which the King not thinking fit to anſwer, ſtill continuing his way, the Souldier believing that it was perhaps <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Theif, who would make uſe of the darkneſs of the night, called his Companion and both together ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the King with much violence; he did all he could to get out of their hands, to the end he might not be known: But it was in vain, and the noiſe they made having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waked moſt part of thoſe who were in the neighbouring apartments who came to help the Sentinels; the King whom they would have killed was conſtrained to make himſelf known. Never were people ſo ſurprized as thoſe Guards were; their boldneſs turned into fear, and they would have fled to avoid the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:150241:57"/>puniſhment they beleived to have merited, when the King command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them to ſtay, and to tell thoſe who came to know what paſſed, that having quarrelled with one another they had cauſed the noiſe that had been heard. As they did not expect to be quit for ſo ſmall a thing, they willingly obeyed, and the King covering his face, and preſſing to know the occaſion of the noiſe, for the better conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, retired to his apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Marchioneſs and <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield</hi> not ſeeing the King come, imagined ſome ill might have happned to him, which made them very uneaſie, eſpecially <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> beginning to have an inclianation for him, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very much concerned. He for his part was no leſs out of humour, whether for not having ſeen his Miſtreſs, or becauſe he feared that adventure coming to be diſcovered,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:150241:58"/>it might break all his meaſures; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he could not ſleep, and kept his bed the following day, loaded with ill humour and vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Baron being recovered he went to ſee the King, who told him what had happned, and that he had only received ſome blows of their fiſts. He was willing to make a Galantry of it to <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> and writ her this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF it be as difficult to engage your heart, as it is uneaſie to ſurprize the vigilance of your Guards, without doubt,</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>you will quickly render me the moſt unfortunate Prince of the world, as you have made me the moſt amorous. I was ſtopped yeſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day evening notwithſtanding all my precautions, I was treated as a Thief, all the Neighbourhood was alarm'd, and I had like to have loſt my life: However, I do not complain, and it is only to put you out of pain that I give
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:150241:58"/>you this notice; for it is ſo pleaſant to ſuffer for what One loves, that I eſteem my ſelf very happy to have been in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: But if after this,</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>you ſtill doubt of the greatneſs of my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and if you perſevere any longer in that coldneſs which makes me diſpair; when I ſee you it will be only to dye at your feet of Grief and of Love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>CASIMER.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The King having given this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Baron, he went immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to the Marchioneſſes, where finding <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> he acquainted them with the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Circumſtances, and gave <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> the King's Letter, it being the firſt he had writ to her ſhe bluſhed, appeared much amazed, and it was with a great deal of fear ſhe opened it. But the Baron preſſing her to give an Anſwer ſhe was in great per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity:
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:150241:59"/>yet after ſeveral irreſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; whether out of reſpect or inclination, ſhe wrote this Letter to the King.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THo the acknowledgment I ought to have of all the favours you haue done me, ſhould not oblige me, Great Prince, to take part in all that concerns you; your life is too dear and too pretious to remain inſenſible when One learns it has been in danger: Wherefore I am as much moved as One can be at the accident that happned to you laſt Night, and as I am the cauſe of it, I cannot tell you preciſely the impreſſion it makes upon my heart: But I can aſſure you that it begins to fear you, and that it will ſuddainly alſo want Guards, if you continue thus to attaque it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> having given this Letter to the Baron, he went immediatly to carry it the King
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:150241:59"/>who was at the Queens apartment. But tho he was uſed to ſtay longer there, his impatience made him go out as ſoon as he perceived the Baron; and hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heart being between fear and hopes, he opened his Miſtreſſes Letter with much preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation; tho it was not very kind, he felt ſo extraordinary a joy that he could not hold from ſhowing it in the leaſt of his actions. In effect it is certain that of all the pleaſures we find in Love, the moſt ſenſible is that which gives the firſt glimpſe of being beloved; for tho thoſe which follow are uſually more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, it may be ſaid however they are not ſo agreeable, and that they are leſs moving to a Lover. The ſame evening the King had a very tender Converſation with <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> who being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing bolder, ſaid to him a thouſand things which made him find her more lovely than he had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore:
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:150241:60"/>inſomuch that he returned the moſt ſatisfied of all men. But if Love was favourable to him, his joy was quickly changed into trouble. The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> did not ſleep, and <hi>Ragieski</hi> had given him too fair hopes for to neglect them. Wherefore he broke the Truce which was to have laſted ſix years longer, as we have ſaid, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all his Deſigns to the Conqueſt of <hi>Poland. Caſimer</hi> in his firſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize offered Peace to the <hi>Coſaques</hi> with a general Pardon, and the Confirmation of their antient Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, and likewiſe the liberty to brew Beer, make Metheglin, and burn Brandy. But he could not reduce thoſe Rebells to their Devoir; and at that time Prince <hi>Charles, Alexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nuis</hi> and of <hi>Plosko,</hi> his only Brother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, few Monarchs have been afflicted like him. This was not yet enough for the ſhaking his
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:150241:60"/>of his great Courage, Prince <hi>James Rodrivil,</hi> One of his Generals, took the part of <hi>Charles</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> after having failed in his duty at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ege of <hi>Mohilon,</hi> and for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleating his misfortune, the <hi>Tartars</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyned to <hi>Caſimer</hi>'s Troops, having <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaten <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> before <hi>Husman,</hi> killed fourteen thouſand men, taken two and twenty Pieces of Canon, as many Colours, and Arms for ſix thouſand Souldiers; they return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into their Country after having ſet <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> at liberty, whom they had alſo taken Priſoner. He ſent the Lords <hi>de Chilmilenski</hi> and <hi>de Norviſcovite</hi> for the States of <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuania</hi> in Embaſſy to <hi>Stockholm,</hi> who offered to <hi>Charles</hi> all he could deſire for the making a good Peace with him: But having anſwered them that he was reſolved to paſs the Sea: Two days after <hi>Charles</hi> departed with an Army of fourteen thouſand men, and the greateſt Lords of his
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:150241:61"/>Kingdom. General <hi>Wittimberg</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded another Army of ſixteen thouſand men, and Count <hi>Magnus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e la Garde</hi> expected alſo in <hi>Liſeland</hi> the Orders of <hi>Charles</hi> with a third Army of fourteen thouſand men. All theſe Forces joyned to thoſe of the Electour of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> which were no Ieſs conſiderable, caſt a terrour and fright thro all <hi>Poland. Caſimer</hi> demanded Succours of the Emperour againſt the <hi>Moſcovites,</hi> and en deavoured to reunite the Nobemen for the ſaving the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publck: But <hi>Ragieski</hi> who was with <hi>Charles,</hi> had ſo alienated them from their duties, that the Poſpolite <hi>Ruſſeniques</hi> would have had another Chief than the King, which cauſed great diſtruſts. The Eccleſiaſticks alſo offered to bring twelve thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men on foot upon condition that <hi>Chriſtopher Peziemski</hi> might command them. Informuch that all being reduced to this State, Count
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:150241:61"/>
               <hi>Magnus</hi> laid ſieg to <hi>Dunembourg,</hi> which the vigorous reſiſtance of the Governour had newly cauſed the <hi>Moſcovites</hi> to quit, and having taken it in few days, it was found that the ſame Governour had been cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and that he was of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with the <hi>Swedes.</hi> General <hi>Wittemberg</hi> was no leſs ſuccesful in upper <hi>Poland;</hi> for tho the four Vaivods were encamped with fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen thouſand men near the River <hi>Notterlach;</hi> they baſely abandoned <hi>Caſimer</hi>'s ſide, without making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defence, and took the Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> upon this Condition amongſt ſeveral others; that if they took 'Arms again for <hi>Caſimer,</hi> their goods ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſcated at the Kings pleaſure. Some ſhort time after this Conqueſt, which gave to the <hi>Swedes</hi> more than forty Leagues of ground without loſing one man: <hi>Charles</hi> came and joyned <hi>Wittenberg</hi> near <hi>Pozen</hi> with twenty
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:150241:62"/>thouſand men; but in ſtead of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Conditions that <hi>Wittem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> had granted, all manner of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olences were committed, and a Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>op had his throat cut for the hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his mony. <hi>Caſimer</hi> being aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned by the greateſt part of his Subjects, and <hi>Charles</hi> become Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of great <hi>Poland,</hi> he marched with all his Troops directly to <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw</hi> for the beſieging it: He ruined all the Cities in his paſſage which made the leaſt reſiſtance, and being at <hi>Colo, Peſiemski</hi> came to him in Quality of <hi>Caſimer</hi>'s Ambaſſador for to demand Peace of him: But <hi>Charles</hi> having made anſwer that he was too near his Coſin not to ſee him, he diſmiſſed him, and told him ſmiling that he hoped to viſit him very ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Caſimer</hi> having no more than fourteen thouſand men, went to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> wherein he put a good Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, and from thence followed the Queen who was upon the way
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:150241:62"/>to <hi>Cracow.</hi> But as all theſe mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes did not leſſen the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs he had for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field,</hi> and that on the contrary ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſeemed to have augmented his flames, he diſpatched the Baron towards the Queen, under pretence of informing her of what paſſed, and encharged him with this Letter for his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DO you remember,</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>the trouble I was in to quit you, and the grief that appeared in my face, when I was as forced from my ſelf to go appoſe the violences of my Enemies, Alas! ſince that fatal day, my good fortune has ſeemed to abandon me, and by the degrees I removed from you, my disgraces have encreaſed as well as my Love: Yes, Mademoiſelle, I ſtill love you more than my life, and with what ill ſucceſs ſoever fate does influence my Arms, I ſhall have conſtancy enough not to complain, provided you do not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:150241:63"/>baniſh me out of your memory: But if I was ſo unhappy as to be forced from thence, I ſhould certainly be diſtracted, and dye for grief: Wherefore if you will preſerve a Prince who adores you, let me know what ſhare I have in your heart, and I hope that if that heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to yeild to the moſt faithful paſſion that ever was, my Enemies will not be able to reſiſt me.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>omoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> being made ſenſible by the Kings misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, was extremely touched to learn all that the inſidelity of his Subjects made him ſuffer. And no longer doubting but that he loved her, ſince he gave her marks of it in the greateſt fatigues of War, would no longer conceal the tender ſentiments of her heart. And the Queen having given her diſpatches to the Baron, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> made the King this Anſwer.</p>
            <pb n="115" facs="tcp:150241:63"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IF the luſtre of your Crown had engaged me to love you, you would have reaſon to apprehend, Great Prince, that the ill ſucceſs of your Arms had done you ſome ill Office in my heart. But as the beautiful Qualities of your mind had only acquired it you, you ought not to fear the being forced from it by ſo ſhameful a way. May your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, Sir, but preſerve your perſon, and I abandon to them both the State and all the world beſides: But, Alas! the dangers I am informed you are ever ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to, give me troubles and allarms, and I ſhall not be at eaſe as long as you are abſent. Ah! if you love me as much as you would perſwade me, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your ſelf Sir I conjure you; and provided I may ſee you ſuddainly I have nothing more to deſire.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>While things ſtood thus between <hi>Caſimer</hi> and his Miſtreſs, the Baron was not ſo well ſatisfied with the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:150241:64"/>Marchioneſs, for having found her in a certain coldneſs, that made him ſuſpect ſome body had made uſe of his abſence, and preſſing her to acquaint him with the cauſe of her change, inſtead of clearing his doubts as formerly, ſhe was ſo vexed he ſhould accuſe her of inconſtancy, that the Baron could not hold from ſaying to her all that jealouſy could inſpire the moſt amorous man with, and would have thus returned to the Army, if <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schenfield,</hi> perceiving their miſintelligence had not reconciled them. But as the Baron had not all the reaſon on his ſide, and that the Marchioneſs ſtill loved him with the ſame conſtancie; he asked her pardon for his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, and returned to the King, who expected him with an extream impatience. As <hi>Wittemberg</hi> perſued <hi>Caſimer, Charles</hi> took <hi>Warſaw</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out much pain, and then having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned the General, he marched
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:150241:64"/>towards <hi>Cracow.</hi> He was n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> m<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his way that <hi>Caſimer</hi> waited for him with an Army of fourteenthou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, he went to ſeek him, he found him, and the Polanders fled and ſaved themſelves in the Woods. Inſomuch that <hi>Charles</hi> laid ſieg to <hi>Cracow</hi> which was valiantly defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But after ſeveral aſſaults, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no hopes of ſuccours, the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon capitulated and yielded at the end of five Weeks. During this ſieg, <hi>Caſimer</hi> was upon the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of <hi>Buck,</hi> where the Baron not having been able to joyn him ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, gave him <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field's</hi> Letter: he received it with all the teſtimonies of joy he was then capable of, and as he found in it all he could deſire, he hoped by the good ſucceſs of his Love, to vanquiſh alſo his Enemies. But having notice that <hi>Charles</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Maſter of the capital City of the Kingdom and of other the moſt
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:150241:65"/>conſiderable Places, would likewiſe endeavour to ſeize his Perſon, he ſent a Courier to the Queen that ſhe might come to him with the Troops ſhe had for her Guard, which having happily performed, <hi>Caſimer</hi> reſolved to retire into <hi>Sileſia</hi> in the Dutchy of <hi>Eopol,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to him. But as he paſſed thro the Frontiers of <hi>Hungary,</hi> a Palatine obliged him to ſtop, and threatned to charge him if he did not retire out of the States of the Emperour. As neeeſſity gives ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients which One would not make uſe of at another time: The King not being able to obtain the paſſage by force, had recourſe to addreſs. He gave an Order in writing to <hi>Morſtain</hi> to go to the Emperour's Court, to offer him his Crown, and <hi>Morſtain</hi> having ſhewn his Order to the Palatine, without further exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the thing, he eſcorted the King as far as <hi>Eopol,</hi> where he ſtill
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:150241:65"/>continued to love and ſee <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield. Charles</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing learnt the retreat of <hi>Caſimer,</hi> and General <hi>Potoski</hi> having been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated near <hi>Cominice</hi> by <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> General of the <hi>Coſaques,</hi> he made uſe of thoſe favourable conjunctures for the continuing his Progreſſes with ſafety. He drew <hi>Chilmilenski</hi> on his ſide, as likewiſe <hi>Charles, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander, Conitspolskin,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Quartains. And as victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry acquires friends, <hi>Ragoski</hi> Prince of <hi>Tranſilvania,</hi> ſent to him alſo Ambaſſadors for their making an Alliance together. The Principal chiefs of the Nobility of little <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> took alſo <hi>Charles</hi> his Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and all but the great Treaſurer of the Kingdom, the Lords, <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neski, Preziemski,</hi> and <hi>Volf</hi> abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Caſimer.</hi> But while every One ſubmitted to <hi>Charles,</hi> and that he cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Diet to be aſſembled at <hi>War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw,</hi> the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:150241:66"/>to aſſure himſelf of <hi>Pruſſia</hi> by the means of Negotiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But the <hi>Dantrichers</hi> having diſcovered his artifices, remained faithful to <hi>Caſimer,</hi> and he referred the declaring himſelf to a more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſeaſon. The <hi>Moſcovites</hi> on their ſide took <hi>Lublin</hi> where they commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unheard of cruelties. The Count of <hi>Steembock</hi> aſiſted by <hi>Ragieski,</hi> preſented himſelf before <hi>Torne,</hi> and the Burghers animated with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrances of this laſt, and with the fair promiſes they made them, rendred without any reſiſtance. <hi>Charles</hi> made his entry therein, and was received with all the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of imaginable joy. But being willing to ſee the Burghers in Arms, he ordered them to carry them to the town-houſe, reproaching that they had defended themſelves too ill, and that he would give them to others who ſhould make better uſe of them. Thus <hi>Charles</hi> puniſhed
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:150241:66"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem the firſt day, for their unfidelity to their King. After this expedition <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e went to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> to aſſiſt there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Diet he had convoqued, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing that the Senators would not fail to offer him the Crown: But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to diſcover the fault they had committed, in not diſputing with <hi>Charles</hi> his entring into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, they did not anſwer his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation: And <hi>Caſimer</hi> having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oqued another Diet at <hi>Eopol,</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and invited the Nobility to come thither; the firſt who appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was the valiant <hi>Charneski</hi> with his Troops; <hi>Volf</hi> would have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with his, but was hindred by the <hi>Swedes.</hi> Nothing could be added to the Careſſes the King made him, and he had great reaſon to do ſo, ſince in the Sequel he was the reſtorer of his affairs. He ſent Ambaſſadors to all the Princes his Allyes to demand ſuccours; that to <hi>Rome</hi> obtained a conſiderable Sum
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:150241:67"/>from the Pope; that to <hi>Vienna</hi> good hopes, and the Queen having ſold all her Jewels, he hoped to put things in a better Poſture. His Court was not very great at <hi>Eopol,</hi> and he needed conſolation for the ſupporting all the diſgraces that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rune had ſent him. He found none greater than the Converſation of <hi>Mademeiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> whom he ſtill loved with much paſſion, and by whom he was likewiſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved. They continued to meet in the Marchioneſſes Apartment: But at length the Queen diſcovered it, ſhe highly reſented this new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigue, and in the firſt tranſport o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> her jealouſy would have removed <hi>Mademaiſelle de Schanfield</hi> from Court, and have ſent back the Marchioneſs into <hi>France.</hi> The King had occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of managing the Queen, and things were no longer in the ſame poſture they were in the time of the Vice-Chancellor's Lady: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:150241:67"/>he uſed peaceable means and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppeaſed the Queen, by promiſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to think no more of <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lle de Schanfield:</hi> The Queen was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tisfied with this promiſe; and <hi>Saſimer</hi> having conſtrained himſelf for ſome days, ſhe eaſily believed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e would keep his word. But as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was not able to live without ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> and that he likewiſe conſidered on the other ſide, that if the Queen ſhould again diſcover that he ſtill loved her, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e would not fail to ſend her back. In this grevious extremity that cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed in him pains that ſenſibly touched his heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he reſolved to marry <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> to the Prince of <hi>Zamoski,</hi> in the opinion he might at leaſt continue to love her, and be beloved; whereas if the Queen ſent her back, which was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>llible, he ſhould loſe her for ever. He communicated this deſign to the Baron, as to the perſon he deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:150241:68"/>for the negotiating this Marriage<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and after having given him all the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary inſtructions for his ſucceeding in it, he ordered him to be ready to go to <hi>Zamoski.</hi> And that it might no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be beleived that this was the occaſion of the Baron's journey thither, he gave him Orders addreſſed to the Prince for the fortifying the Place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Marchioneſs was of the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; neither did the Baron make any difficulty to diſcover to her his buſineſs. The voyage was long and dangerous, ſhe could not forbea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> being greived, and ſhed tears; the Baron was alſo concerned; and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> having found them in this poſture, knew not to what ſhe ſhould attribute this great ſadneſs. Wherefore ſhe asked them very obligingly what was the cauſe of it, and aſſured them if ſhe could contribute to their ſatisfaction, ſhe would do it with all her heart. The Marchioneſs madeſome difficulty to
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:150241:68"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll it her, apprehending the King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould take it ill; But in fine <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oiſelle de Schanfield</hi> preſſed her with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good a grace, and with ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rneſtneſs, that the Marchioneſs did really avow to her what was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>bject of their greif. Yes, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle,</hi> added the Marchioneſs, we are only afflicted for your ſake, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f I loved you leſs, I could with more caſe bear with your removeal. They talk of marrying you, the Baron has Orders to negotiate your marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, and perhaps he will innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contribute to the rendering you unfortunate the reſt of your days; for it is very uneaſie to diſengage One's heart when it is fixed by ſuch pleaſing tyes as are thoſe of a great Prince, who loves you, or rather who adores you; and when One is ſenſible, it is very hard to be on a ſuddain under the laws of a husband, who never having been a Lover, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periouſly uſes the power he has over
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:150241:69"/>us. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> who knew nothing yet of the deſign the King had of marrying her, was ſo ſurprized with the Marchioneſſes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, that ſhe eyed her a long time, after a manner that made her judge ſhe had ſpoke too much; For that fair Perſon after having chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed colour ſeveral times, fell into a ſwoon into the Marchioneſſes arms, and when ſhe came to her ſelf, ſhe could only ſay theſe ſad words! Ha! Sir, ſince you do not love me, why will you render me unhahpy! and then fainted the ſecond time; But in fine the tears which fell from her fair Eyes, having ſomething recovered her from her ſurprize, ſhe ſaid the moſt moveing things imaginable; and the Baron and Marchioneſs could not forbear mingling their tears with thoſe of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield.</hi> It was the uſual hour that <hi>Caſimer</hi> came to ſee her, he entered the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber they were in without their tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:150241:69"/>notice of it; He was not a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le amazed to ſee them all three in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat poſture, and not being able to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>magine the cruſe, he ſtood as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ovable; the Baron being the firſt that perceived him, roſe immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y to give him a Chair, thoſe two lovely perſons did all that they could to recover their briskneſs, fancying the King had not ſeen them, and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> being willing to turn the thing into Rallery, told him, truly, S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, it is not civil to ſurprize Ladies thus, and to walk as ſoftly as if you were to paſs by Sentinels in your way to a Randevouze; the King remembring the danger he had been in, told her, that he was no leſs grieved than the day he was ſo ill treated, ſince that having found her crying without knowing the Cauſe, he ſtopped, not being able to walk. But if you love me, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle,</hi> added he, as much you
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:150241:70"/>would perſwade me you do, you ſhould acquaint me with the occaſion of it, if it depends on me, it not being juſt you ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal the thoughts to the perſon in the world, who takes moſt part in all that concerns you: Sir, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Charming Maid, it is ſo natural to thoſe of our ſex to have Compaſſion of perſons that are ill treated, that the Baron <hi>de Saint-Cir</hi> having made us the recital of a very tragical ſtory that he had learnt, we could not forbear ſhedding tears, and I am certain tho you are leſs tender than we, you would have been no leſs concerned; This, Sir, was the Cauſe of our ſadneſs, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing being able to grieve me long, while that your Majeſty ſhall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour me with looking upon me fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably. But if I was ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate that you ſhould reſolve toaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, I avow to you that I ſhould never be able to receive any ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:150241:70"/>I beleive, replyed <hi>Caſimer,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mething bluſhing, that you are ſo juſt as to allow, that from the time I have loved you, I have done all that depends on me, to perſwade you that you are the deareſt perſon to me in the world: and thus I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee how I could reſolve to aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don you, ſeeing if I had the thoughts of it, I ſhould render my ſelf more unhappy than you. Wherefore be aſſured that let what will happen I ſhall never forget you; but after this aſſurance that I make you, do not find, it ſtrange (at theſe words he made a deep ſigh) that I my ſelf acquaint you with a piece of news, that will without doubt as much ſurprize you, as it has a long time afflicted me. You know that the Queens jealouſly moves her to ſend you back to your Relations; I ſhall not brag of what I have done to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, it being uſeleſs: But app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending that at length ſhe may
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:150241:71"/>come to that extemity, I have reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to get you a Husband. How! Sir, replyed impatiently, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> could you take ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, after all the Proteſtations I have ſo often made you of never marrying. Ah! If you loved me you would not give me to an Other. No, Sir, you do not love me, you ever deceived me when you told me you loved me. When we are deep in love, we always know how to find the means of preſerving what we love. Love never fails ſuch as are faithful to him; and it is in thoſe occaſions he ſhews his Power. But if you have been able to faile in your word to him, beleive, Sir, added ſhe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I will keep mine with him, and that my Conſtancy ſhall reproach you with your infidelity. What you ſay, anſwered <hi>Caſimer,</hi> wholly amazed, is too advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for me to blame it, and I ever expected this uſage from you. But
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:150241:71"/>if you make but the leaſt Reflexion upon the neceſſity I am in of having you married, or of loſing you, for ever I beleive that you will grant that what you call a defect of love in me, is one of the greateſt marks of paſſion I can give you in ſo ill a juncture. For as Love ought not only to conſiſt in loving the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who loves us with all the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs and paſſion they are capable of, but that we ought likewiſe to love their Reputations, and all that can be advantageous to them, tho it may be ſometimes repugnant to our inclinations. It is certain that if we act otherwiſe, and that we on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider our pleaſures as the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly objects of our paſſion, it would be rather a ſelf love than a real affection. And thus you ſee, <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle,</hi> that it is love maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by reaſon that obliges me to act in this manner. I very well know you may anſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is no great
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:150241:72"/>ſign of Love, to reſolve to ſhare with an other what we ought to poſſeſs alone, and that this may be even called by the name of a Civil falling out. But not only beleiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you to be too juſt as to have one thought which would be ſo diſadvantagious to me, my dignity would ſhelter me from that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, ſince that Kings, tho Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aigns, may not act as other men. Their hearts as well as others are ſuſceptible of all paſſions; they love, and yet their greatneſs which ought to be a help to them with their Miſtreſſes, is what the moſt ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines them. The Queen knows I love you as much as one can love, and notwithſtanding the promiſes I made her, ſhe cannot fail of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering that I do not keep them. She would ſend you back to your Relations, they would put you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Convent, both the one or the other would equally injure your
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:150241:72"/>reputation, and would deprive me of ever ſeeing you. Wherefore I cannot do better either for you or my ſelf, than to marry you within my Kingdom: I have caſt my eyes upon Prince <hi>Zamoski,</hi> who might make an other happy, and I will ſo ſtrongly engage him in the Court, that we ſhall be both of us happy. Reſiſt no longer to give your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, keep it ſecret, and do not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me of inconſtancy and of hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing little love. Sir, replyed <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfeild,</hi> who was ſtill weeping, ſince your paſſion muſt ſtoop to the Queens jealouſy, and that I muſt part from you, permit me to ſhut my ſelf up in a Convent, rather then to ſee my ſelf under the power of a Husband, whoſe Capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio would be without doubt fatal to me; in ſuch a place I ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie my inclination and what I owe to you; and if I may not have the liberty of ſeeing you, at leaſt
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:150241:73"/>I ſhall have the joy of giving you all my thoughts, you ſhall ever Reign in my heart notwithſtanding the Queens tranſports: Love ſhall not be ſhared with divorce, and in fine the hopes I ſhall be in, that you will ever love me, will make me ſuffer my diſgrace with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and without complaining. <hi>Caſimer</hi> ſeeing this reſiſtance, was in a ſtrange perplexity, and his Soul divided between love and fear, made him take a thouſand different Reſolutions; but after having kept ſilence ſome time, he anſwered with a tone that made apparent the pain he was in. As the repoſe both of your life and mine is concerned in the choice you are to make, I ſhould be too unjuſt, if I obliged you to give me inſtantly a poſitive anſwer. I leave you alone to think of it ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, but eſpecially remember, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> that liberty is the greateſt happineſs, and that you
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:150241:73"/>will have no ſooner loſt it in ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting your ſelf up in a Cloiſter, than that you will make uſeleſs vowes for the recovering it. In ſiniſhing theſe words, <hi>Caſimer</hi> not being able to continue this converſation, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bid the Baron follow him, he left <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfeild</hi> with the Marchioneſs in an unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible affliction. As he was no leſs agitated for his part, he was a long time without ſpeaking, but after much walking, he acquainted the Baron with the Cauſe of his diſquiet, and ordred him to be ready to depart in four dayes, and in the mean time to uſe all his endeavours with <hi>Mademoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelle de Schanfeild</hi> to get her conſent to this marriage. After which he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed him. The Baron returned to the Marchioneſs, whom he found all alone, and having with grief acquainted her, that the King was reſolved he ſhould depart without delay (which extremity ſurprized
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:150241:74"/>her, ſhe expecting his paſſion for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> would have made him change his deſign; he alſo retired to his lodging. Sleep; which eaſes the moſt ſtirring griefs; was not that night known by thoſe four perſons, who having all their ſeveral afflictions, paſſed it in that trouble that is eaſie to be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended: So that the day hardly began to appear, than that <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield</hi> went to the Marchioneſs extremely dejected: There was no longer ſeen in her fair Eyes that ſparkling that made their glances hardly to be ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and her whole perſon was ſo languiſhing, that ſhe would have inſpired Compaſſion in the moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vage minds. She no ſooner ſaw the Marchioneſs, who was in bed, than that ſhe ſaid to her, with the moſt moveing air imaginable; well Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, have you found any remedy to my misfortune, or will you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:150241:74"/>with me, that never any one was greater, and that on what ſide ſoever I look, I find my ſelf unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? I grant, anſwered the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs, that you are much to be pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied, and that a heart muſt be hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than Marble, that is infenſible to your juſt grief. I do certainly take all the part that a real friend ought to take in it, and it has ſo diſquieted me all the night that I could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly ſhut my Eyes. But as of two ills the leaſt is to be choſen, I ſtill think it better to marry, than to be ſhut all ones life in a Convent: For tho our liberties be engaged in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, and that we are obliged to ſupport the ill humours of our huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, and ſometime their contempt, we do not however ſo abſolutely loſe it, but that there remains that of telling him our ſentiments; and for the finding the means of ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying our inclinations, a little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance when we cannot have Love,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:150241:75"/>may lul a ſleep his vigilance, if he be of a jealous humour, and even very often get into his confidence, how moroſe ſoever he may be; In fine, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> you will be at Court, you will ſee the King there, and methinks this is not to be very much a ſlave: But in a Convent you cannot do the like, you muſt give an account of all your actions to your Superior, never ſee any body, but by her permiſſion: and that which I find moſt inſupportable is, that you muſt paſs your whole life without being ſuffered to follow your will! It is for you, <hi>Mademoiſelle,</hi> to determine and ſee which you like beſt, for the Baron muſt depart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in four days to go to Prince <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moski,</hi> whom the King deſigns you; and if you would follow my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, added the Marchioneſs, you ſhould choſe this Party. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> was a long time with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anſwering otherwiſe than by
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:150241:75"/>ſighs, which ſhewed the condition her heart was in; but after having ſaid a great many things more, which made appear the cruel agitation this choiſe reduced her to: In fine ſhe reſolved rather to pleaſe the King, than out of any inclination ſhe had to Wedlock, to marry Prince <hi>Zamoski.</hi> The Baron coming in a moment after, the Marchioneſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed him that <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> would ſubmit to the King's will. He thinking to carry him wellcome News, went immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give him an account of it: But he found this Prince in ſo unequal a dipoſition of mind, that tho he had declared to him the evening before, that he deſired nothing with more paſſion than to ſee <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> in the Reſolution ſhe was now in; <hi>Caſimer</hi> appeared however ſo extremely afflicted at it, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having walked ſome time with precipitation; how unhappy am I!
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:150241:76"/>cried he on a ſuddain, to labour with earneſtneſs for what will coſt me ſo much grief: I oblige a perſon who loves me, to put her ſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her will under the laws of a Husband, and yet I cannot be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent that ſhe grants me what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of her. Ah! how true it is, added he a moment after, that Love and Reaſon are incompatible: From whence proceeds it that I have ſo little reſolution after having had the power of making my ſelf ſuch a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition: It is without doubt ſome good genius that expreſly occaſions my irreſolutions, to ſet my mind at reſt, by preſerving my Miſtreſs: But alſo what will the Queen ſay? What will ſhe not do, if ſhe perceives I have failed in my word to her? as it is impoſſible but that I muſt fail: She will ſhut up my Miſtreſs, or ſend her away for ever; I ſhall ſee her no more, and I ſhall dye for grief: No, no, I muſt keep to my firſt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:150241:76"/>as being moſt juſt, ſince in marrying out <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> I ſhall content the Queen, and ſtill poſſeſs her heart. But alas! replyed this amourous King, ſighing, Who will aſſure me that this heart will be ſtill faithful to me when it is engaged? Prince <hi>Zamoski</hi> is young, handſome, lovely, ſhe may love him, and would have reaſon to do ſo: Why am not I in his place? and can One be more unfortunate! After having ſtill held ſome ſuch like diſcourſes as theſe, he told the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron that if he had been ſo long a time without giving him an anſwer, it: was becauſe he had much ado to vanquiſh ſome ſcruples he ſtill had, but that he ſhould depart within two days at the fartheſt for <hi>Zamos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi.</hi> In effect <hi>Caſimer</hi> gave him his Orders for the Prince, and the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Saint-Cir</hi> having ſetled his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, he begun his journey the day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for <hi>Zamoski.</hi> If the King was much
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:150241:77"/>afflicted by being forced to marry his Miſtreſs for the preſerving her, he was no leſs at the news of the continuation of his Enemies Progreſs. <hi>Charles</hi> had not found at <hi>Warſaw</hi> what he had promiſed himſelf, but fortune gave him the coſolation of redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the City of <hi>Elbing,</hi> which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the example of <hi>Torne,</hi> thro the Treachery of a Burgher-Maſter they had corrupted. <hi>Charles</hi> was received there in Triumph, and this happy ſucceſs was followed by another, which being more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous, might abſolutely have ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Caſimer.</hi> The Elector of <hi>Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgh</hi> had not yet declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and remained in <hi>Pruſſia</hi> with his Troops. <hi>Charles</hi> divided his in two, of which he ſent one part to beſiege <hi>Marrembourg,</hi> and with the other he went directly into <hi>Ducall Pruſſia,</hi> where the Quartians made great ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vages. He met <hi>Count Mgnus de la Garde</hi> in <hi>Lifeland,</hi> with an Army of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:150241:77"/>eighteen thouſand men, which he joyned to his own, and made known to the Elector if he would not take his part, he would beſiege <hi>Koningiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and ruin his Province. The Elector declared he would defend himſelf; but <hi>Charles</hi> approaching within five Leagues of <hi>Koninsberg,</hi> He made <hi>Charles</hi> God-father to his Son, and the Elector was the like to his. Chancellor <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onstierne</hi> went to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the King's part, and carried him ſuch an anſwer as he deſired. The King and the Elector conferred at <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtain</hi> with teſtimonies of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and joy, which promiſed no leſs than the ſhareing of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Poland:</hi> They made a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Alliance together, by which amongſt other things the Elector acknowledged the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> the Lord of the fier for <hi>Ducal Pruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia.</hi> And in acknowledgment <hi>Charles</hi> granted to the Elector the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prick
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:150241:78"/>of <hi>Varminia,</hi> in reſerve of <hi>Bronsberg,</hi> a very Catholick City, and a Univerſity of the <hi>Polanders.</hi> The States of the Country were not very well ſatisfied, but they could not hinder it: The Elector re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Koningsberg,</hi> where he cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be publiſhed that all the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers who ſhould refuſe to make Oath to the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> ſhould retire. Inſomuch that <hi>Caſimer</hi> had no more left than the Cities of <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zight,</hi> and <hi>Mariemburg.</hi> The firſt rendred its fidelity remarkable to Poſterity, the Inhabitants ſet fire on their Suburbs, and what promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſoever that were made them of preſerving their Priviledges, and even of augmenting them, they were unalterable in the Reſolution they had taken of defending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the laſt extremity. This City is the largeſt, moſt powerful, and has the greateſt Commerce of all thoſe of the North, and the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:150241:78"/>Magiſtrates ſeeing their King aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and without forces to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour them, augmented their Troops, ſent Deputies to the <hi>Hague</hi> for the remonſtrating to the States the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt they had to aid them, that the liberty of Commerce might be preſerved; and in fine they omitted nothing that might conduce to their maintenance. Yet <hi>Charles</hi> had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Partiſans who powerfully ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balled for the making him Maſter of that important Place: They decry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Caſimer</hi> in all kinds, even accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him that he would exterminate all thoſe who were not Catholiques, and this began to make for his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage: But befides that <hi>Caſimer</hi> deſtroyed thoſe impoſtures by the Letters he ſent to the Magiſtrates, to whom he promiſed powerful ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours: The people of <hi>Danzick</hi> having learnt that <hi>Charles</hi> had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armed the Burghers of <hi>Tornes,</hi> and done ſome other things contrary to
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:150241:79"/>the terms of the Capitulation; this ſo animated them againſt him, that they begun to decry him, and cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a new Oath to be taken to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend themſelves without being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to propoſe yeilding upon pain of Death. <hi>Charles</hi> having left General <hi>Steembock</hi> before <hi>Mariem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> and ſettled all in <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> went into <hi>Poland</hi> for to chaſe <hi>Caſimer</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely away, who was gathering Troops upon the Frontiers of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary</hi> to try the recovery of what he had loſt. Some of the Nobility beginning to be weary of the <hi>Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh</hi> yoke, having joyned <hi>Caſimer,</hi> he ſent <hi>Morſtein</hi> to the great Cham of <hi>Tartary</hi> to demand of him ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours, and obtained forty thouſand Horſe, and <hi>Charneski</hi> having made a Body of four and twenty Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netts of <hi>Cavellery,</hi> without Canon, and without Infantry. <hi>Charles</hi> quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Warſaw,</hi> and went to ſeek him with all his Troops in the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:150241:79"/>of <hi>Lublin.</hi> Tho <hi>Charles</hi> was Inferiour in Troops to <hi>Caſimer,</hi> his great courage obliged him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight. The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he right wing of the Battaile to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ittemberg,</hi> and the left wing to <hi>Duglas.</hi> The two Armies met, the Shocque was terrible, and the <hi>Swedes</hi> who were not uſed to find reſiſtance, were ſurprized at that they met with. <hi>Charneski</hi> being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to revenge <hi>Caſimer,</hi> did all he could to find out <hi>Charles;</hi> more than twelve hundred Swedes fell by their ſables, Prince <hi>Adolphus</hi> was wounded in the knee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to return to <hi>Warſaw:</hi> The King was likewiſe in very great danger; but in fine <hi>Charneski</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he could not joyn him, and fearing to be ſurrounded, made his paſſage with his ſable in his hand and retracted, after having given marks of an extraordinary valour. The loſs was almoſt equal, and the <hi>Polan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:150241:80"/>flight was much more preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to them than the battail, of which the King of <hi>Swedon</hi> had how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the glory. <hi>Charneski<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> retreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Samoski,</hi> where the Baron <hi>de Saint-Cir</hi> had delivered his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches to Prince <hi>Zanoski,</hi> who cauſed the fortifications to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, which <hi>Charneski</hi> found in a good poſture, and while that he made his Troops repoſe there, the Baron acquitted himſelf with ſucceſs of the Commiſſion that <hi>Caſimer</hi> had given him. In effect the Prince having asking him the News of what paſſed at <hi>Caſimers</hi> Court, the Baron cunningly made him ſo advantageous a diſcription of <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield</hi> that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a great eſteem for her. Some dayes after falling again upon the ſame diſcourſe, he ſo exaggerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Ladies Beauty and the other Qualities of her wit, that the Prince ſeemed deſirous to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:150241:80"/>ſee her; to which the Baron hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made anſwer that he might do it if he pleaſed, and even marry her, being aſſured that the King would conſent to it. Perceiving that this diſcourſe was not unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the Prince, he alſo offered to make the propoſitions, and to negotiate the thing; aſſuring him that being a great Prince, and very rich, he could not do better than to take a Wife who would render him the happieſt of all men. The Baron puſhed the thing further and ſo inflamed the Prince for <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> that he obliged him to write her this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOur Beauty makes ſo much noiſe and it is maintained by ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>erit that it is not to be wondred,</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>if notwithſtanding the furies of the Warr you create a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers. For my part, to whom all fine things are infinitely agreeable, I really
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:150241:81"/>avow that the deſcription that has been made me of your perſon, has depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me of my heart and Liberty. If this Confeſſion does not diſpleaſe you,</hi> Mademoiſelle, <hi>and that you will give me leave to come and confirm to you my deſeat, I dare aſſure you that of all thoſe who have the honour to wear your Chains, there is not one who is more perfectly ſubdued than</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Prince <hi>Zareoski.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Baron <hi>de Saint Cir</hi> having received this Letter from the Prince, ſent it to <hi>Mademeiſelle de Schanfield</hi> who ſhewed it the King. But the Queen having diſcovered the true occaſion of the Baron's voyage, and not being willing to ſuffer that <hi>Mudemoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> ſhould be ſo well ſetled, ſentan other Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to <hi>Zamoski</hi> for to perſwade the Prince from this marriage, and propoſe to him that of another Maid of Honour called <hi>Mademei.
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:150241:81"/>ſelle d' Arquiem</hi> by birth a French-Woman. This <hi>Mademoiſelle de Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouiem</hi> was no leſs beautiful than <hi>Mademoifelle de Schanfield,</hi> and had likewiſe the advantage of being much in the Queens favour. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Caſimer</hi> gave the Baron no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it with order to traverſe this Envoy, and to make known to the Prince that he acted with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his orders. He alſo writ to <hi>Zamoski</hi> that he approved his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field.</hi> And that he might the more engage him, he conſented ſhe ſhould make the following anſwer.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>I <hi>Did not expect, My Lord, to make conqueſts ſo far off, nor ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable as thoſe you have done me the Honour to mention; and I had hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto believed my ſolf ſo much below the praiſes that you give me, that if an other Prince had made me ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurances, I ſhould have been farr from
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:150241:82"/>having thoughts of meriting them. But My Lord, I find my ſelf ſo inclined to give credit to perſons of your rank, that if you never ſo little continue to wiſh me well, I ſhall have reaſon to think my ſelf perfectly happy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Letter and the Queens envoy arrived almoſt at the ſame time at <hi>Zamosk,</hi> and the Prince appeared ſo well ſatisfied with the wit of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> that the Baron believed him, too much in love to forbear marrying her. But as the Envoy ſpoke no leſs advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageouſly of <hi>Mademoiſelle d' Arquiem,</hi> the Prince ſeemed very much per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed, eſpecially becauſe the Queen propoſed to him the marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this laſt, and the giving him proportionable advantages. The Baron endeavoured to deſtroy all that the Envoy had done, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring to the Prince that his glory was concerned not to appear incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:150241:82"/>that the King might likewiſe be offended with his procedure; and in fine that the offers the Queen made him would more ſtain his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation than they would be of advantage to him; that ſuch great Lords as he ought never to do any thing out of intereſt. Theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons were convincing, the Prince made reflection on them, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Queens Envoy with much indifference in all the other Conferences they had together. But that which quite determined the Prince in favour of <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> was a piece of the Barons cunning. He was uſed to play very often with <hi>Zamoski,</hi> as well for the diverting him, as becauſe it gave him the more liberty to tell him his ſentiments, and in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect he had acquired by theſe means a great familiarity with him. The Baron had ſome dayes before loſt a Diſcretion to that Prince, he
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:150241:83"/>thought to acquit himſelf of it handſomely the Conjuncture ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing too favourable to him for to neglect it. Wherefore he cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly made the Prince accuſe him of not being punctual in paying. And after having accuſed himſelf of the impoſſbility of finding any thing that was agreeable to him, he took out a fine embroidered, Purſe, in which was <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fields</hi> Picture, and giving it to the Prince he told him; I hope my Lord, you will grant one cannot be too diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet when a preſent is to be made ſo conſiderable as that I offer you; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I know added the Baron ſmil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if what I offer you in my purſe may not make you uneaſiy. The Prince whom theſe words made very curious, haſtily opened the Purſe, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving taken out of it <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfie'ds</hi> Picture (which was in a little golden Box ſet with Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds) he appeared in ſo great an
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:150241:83"/>aſtoniſhment that he remained <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> long time immovable. And his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize continuing, the Baron being deſirous to know his opinion, told him, well my Lord, could I have given you a finer thing? I am ſo Charmed, anſwered the Prince, I have not words capable of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you nor of expreſſing my joy; but is it poſſible that the Original of this picture is as hanſome as the Painter repreſents herd far more, replied the Baron, for tho art en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to imitate nature, and that Painters are uſually great flatterers, I dare aſſure you that there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain features in <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field's</hi> face which are ſo fine, and delicate, and ſo much ſparkling in her Eyes, that it is impoſſible for the moſt able Painters to deſcribe them. Thus you ſee, my Lord, that I have not ſurprized you, and what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſoever the Queen propoſes, ſhe can never make any that approaches
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:150241:84"/>the ſatisfaction you will have in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing that fair perſon, whoſe Wit is anſwerable to the Charms of her face. The Baron finding the Prince diſpoſed to hear him favourably, and to believe what he ſaid, added ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other things to what I have mentioned, inſomuch that at length <hi>Zamoski</hi> diſmiſſed the Queens Envoy, to whom he declared he had other engagements he could not break. The Queen was too haughty to be therewith ſatisfied, and fancying her Envoy had not acquitted himſelf well of his Commiſſion, ſhe found the means of cauſing Prince <hi>Zamoski</hi> to come to Court, in the opinion he could not reſiſt what ſhe ſhould tell him her ſelf. The Baron accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied the Prince, and his voyage was not approved of by <hi>Caſimer,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could not openly oppoſe the Queens Will; Yet he received him with teſtimonies of eſteem which made appear the great conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:150241:84"/>he had for him. The Queen for her part forgot nothing that might engage him to marry <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem,</hi> and to that end was more civil to him than ſhe would otherwiſe have been: Inſomuch that the Prince might have thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very happy, if he had not fallen as much in love with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem</hi> as he was already with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield.</hi> But as he could marry but One, and that he was preſſed to determine the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty he was in, rendred him the moſt reſtleſs of all men. He went to viſit thoſe two fair Ladies one after the other, regularly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day, and as <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> ſpoke to him with more liberty than the other did, by reaſon of the Letters that had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, ſhe reproached him ſo agreably with his inconſtancy, or rather to ſay his irreſolution, that as long as he was with her, he did not
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:150241:85"/>think that <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem</hi> was in the world. And as he was very handſome, and had about a million of livres a year, and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed very paſſionate, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> began really to love him, and to reſolve to poſſeſs him entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem</hi> was younger, but the Queen was a good Miſtreſs, and as ſhe had commanded her to be very complaiſant to the Prince, tho before ſhe had been more enclined for young <hi>Zobieski,</hi> to whom ſhe had even promiſed her in marriage: When that <hi>Zamoski</hi> took his turn to viſit <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem,</hi> that baſhfulneſs which is almoſt inſeparable to all young per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſo charmed the Prince, that he was ever as well contented with his two Miſtreſſes as he was diſſatisfied with himſelf. <hi>Caſimer</hi> perceiving <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfields</hi> inclination, ſuffered no leſs on his ſide than the Prince did on his, and there was
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:150241:85"/>this diffence between their paines, that the King could not complain with Juſtice of the ills he endured, becauſe he himſelf was the cauſe of them. <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> and <hi>Mademoiſelle d' Arquiem,</hi> who had thitherto agreed very well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, could not forbear being jealous of one another, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted for the preference, and each of them thought to merit more than her Companion, inſomuch that notwithſtanding the ill ſucceſſes of the War, all this intrigue did not faile to give delight, and to render the Court agreeable. <hi>Caſimer</hi> was the firſt who was weary of it, he could not conceal his jealouſy from the Baron, and the Baron had too much Complaiſance to let the King ſuffer any longer. So that he found the meanes of carrying the Prince back to <hi>Zamoski,</hi> notwithſtanding the defire he had to ſtay at Court. The Queen did all ſhe could to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:150241:86"/>him, But the Baron who had rendred himſelf very agreeable to the Prince, remonſtrated to him, that he ought for his Honours ſake to returne, that he might avoid the affront he would infallibly do one of thoſe Ladies, if he reſolved to marry, in fine they went back to <hi>Zamoſch.</hi> The Prince, who was paſſionately in love, was no ſooner arrived there, than that he would have returned. Tho the Baron re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated that it would do him an extream injury; all this did not perſwade him from his Reſolution. Inſomuch that not being able to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his depart, he gave the King notice of it, who ordered him to ſtay at <hi>Zamoſch</hi> to defend it againſt the <hi>Swedes</hi> who were to attack it: This News put the Prince into the worſt humour imaginable, he found nothing pleaſant, and he would have fancyed it had been done on purpoſe, if the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:150241:86"/>not ſome dayes after effectually ſent Troops to inveſt the place. As it was of extream importance to the Republick, the approach of theſe forces cauſed ſome trouble in him at firſt in the opinion he had the Sieg would employ him a long time. But the intereſt of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and his own Glory having ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended for a time the impetuous motions of his paſſion, he apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf very ſeriouſly to the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the neceſſary orders for the making a vigorous Reſiſtance. In effect the promiſes that were made him did neither ſhake his Courage nor fidelity, Inſomuch that the King reſolved to make that ſiege in perſon. He himſelf aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all the Quarters for his Army, he cauſed the lines of Circonvalati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be made with an admirable promptneſs, and as he went to view the place and to appoint one for the raiſing a Battery, having a Scarlet
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:150241:87"/>Coat on with a white Feather in his Hat, a Canonnier of the Town who knew him by theſe markes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there were ſeveral Officers near his Perſon, pointed his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo right, that one of thoſe who talked to the King was killed, and with the ſame ſhot this Prince fell, and was above an hour in a Swoon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſign of Life. Being how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever recovered from his Swoon and not wounded, he continued with eagerneſs what he had begun, and having opened the Trenches with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Muſquet ſhot, he preſſed the place in ſuch a manner that it made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear the extream deſire he had to take it. As it had five Baſtions, and was environed on one ſide with a very deep Pond and of a very great breadth, that there was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe outworks in a Condition of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting ſome dayes, between two and three thouſand as well Burghers as Souldiers for to defend it, with all
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:150241:87"/>ſort of proviſion and Ammunition in abundance. The Prince was not at all aſtoniſhed at the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence nor at the number of his Troops. He was young and vigorous and one of the braveſt men of the Nation. He was ſeconded by the Baron <hi>de Saint-Cir,</hi> and the Love he had for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> who then alone Reigned in his heart, being joyned to his great Courage, it may be ſaid he undertook ſuprizing things. <hi>Charles</hi>'s Troops had but thitherto met with effiminacy, and found by ſome ſallies that were made upon them, that the <hi>Polanders</hi> are not a people to be eaſily Conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when they are well headed and well united. Several <hi>Swedes</hi> loſt there lives, and in the three dayes the King ſpent in taking the outworks, he loſt above a thouſand men. The Prince was more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned that he learnt no news of his Miſtreſs then he was for the well
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:150241:88"/>defending his Town: and as he had promiſed her to returne ſuddainly to Court, and that he could not make known to her what it was that bindred, the fear he was in ſhe ſhould think him unfaithful, put him into an extream pain, he could not forbear making it known to the Baron, and being one night retired together to take reſt: Am not I very unfortunate, ſaid he to him, to ſee my ſelf in the impoſſibility of keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my word with the moſt lovely perſon that ever was, will ſhe not have reaſon to believe that I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithful, and to loſe all that eſteem and kindneſs ſhe hath ſhowed me with ſo much goodneſs? I confeſs my Lord anſwered the Baron, that <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield</hi> not knowing you are beſeiged, may perhaps complain you have forgot her. And having that conſideration ſhe has for you, her complaints would be well enough grounded. Yet as the King will
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:150241:88"/>not fail of being informed of the condition we are in, I dare aſſure you that ſhe will no ſooner know it than that her fear with be diſſipated, and ſhe will make vows in your favour. The Baron had hardly pronounced theſe laſt words, when one of the Princes Gentlemen entred on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain into the Chamber they were in, and told him that the Enemies tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the occaſion of the mighty dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the night, having ſeized on the Counterſcarpe of the great Baſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, began allready to lodge; that on the Pond ſide they had done the like, and that in fine if they did not haſten to repulſe them, it was to be feard it would much advance the taking of the Town. Any other than the Prince might with juſtice have been allarmed at this Newes. But having told the Baron that after having chaced away the Enemies they would continue their diſcourſe, he cauſed his Armes immediately to
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:150241:89"/>be brought, and without the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of any concerne in his face having drawn up his people, he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided them into two Troops, and having put himſelf at the head of one of them, and given the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the other to the Baron: <hi>Flambeaux</hi> were lighted upon the Walls, and the firſt diſcharge was made ſo luckily upon thoſe that laboured on the lodgings, that in leſs than a quarter of an hour the Counterſcarpe was almoſt Covered with the dead and wounded. The Baron likewiſe behaved himſelf ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirably well on the Pond ſide, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the Enemies notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their Canon and Bombs, were ſo vigourouſly repulſed, and with ſo much loſs, that <hi>Charles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to diſpair of taking the Place, which he thought to have won in eight dayes. However the Canon having made three great Breaches the day after, and <hi>Charles</hi> imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:150241:89"/>that the Bombs had deſolated the City, out of a kind of Raillery ſent to demand of the Prince if he deſired a truce for the putting the Ladies out of fear and in ſafety: But as he had taken ſuch order that neither the Canon or Bombs cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed almoſt any dammage; he let the King know that be thanked him for his generoſity, that the Canon had only killed one old Woman, and that if he made no greater ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts with his forces he hoped in few dayes he might likewiſe offer him a truce for the giving him time to bury the dead and retreat in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Tho the King was extreame haughty he ſeemed not at all vexed at this generous anſwer, and being willing to uſe his utmoſt endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours for the winning the place, The gave orders for a general attack. He had in his Army three thouſand <hi>Jews</hi> whom he had forced to take Arms, and to lay by Commerce
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:150241:90"/>which that Nation is wholy addict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to. Eſpecially in <hi>Poland</hi> where they are very numerous, and where all manner of Religions are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Theſe Jews commanded by the Swediſh Officers were the firſt that mounted to the attaque by three ſeveral places. But whether they were not yet well martialized, or that the courage of the beſieged augmented out of the neceſſity of fighting for the defence of their Walls; it is certain that almoſt all thoſe Infidels were killed upon the place, and in that occaſion the King loſt above four thouſand men: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he believ'd it a diſhonour to him to raiſe the ſieg, and not being willing to omit any thing for the ſucceeding in his Enterprize, he ſent a Trompetter to the Town Gate to demand to ſpeak with the Prince, who was in his Cabinet with the Baron <hi>de Saint-Cir,</hi> where they were contriving together for the finding
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:150241:90"/>ſome Expedient to learn news of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> with whom he became daily more in love than he had ever been: Whereupon he gave Orders the Trompeter ſhould be brought as near as could be to the great Baſtion, which being done, the Prince went thither incontinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, where after having made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf known, the Trompeter told him that the King before he would make the utmoſt trial for the taking him and his town, deſired to have a Conference with him, and to that end he might come into his Camp in all ſafety, and that he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a diſcourſe of two hours would terminate great differences, and ſave the lives of ſeveral perſons. That if he made difficulty to rely upon the word of ſo great a King, he would ſend one of his Officers to acquaint him with his intentions. The Prince perceiving that for want of force, <hi>Charles</hi> would uſe addreſs
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:150241:91"/>and endeavour to ſurprize him, was upon the point of ſending the Trompeter back without an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. But his Town being in a very good poſture, and the abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of all things there ſo great, that they found wherewith to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy themſelves with as much profuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as if it had not been beſieged, he imagined that what the King thought would be favourable to him, would certainly oblige him to raiſe his ſieg by the faithful account the Officer ſhould give him. Wherefore he called a Council of War, that he might not be reproached with any thing, and having in few words expoſed what we have now rola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it was reſolved the King ſhould be allowed to ſend an Officer: The Prince let the Trompeter know, he ſhould return with that account to his Maſter. And half an hour after returning with Col. <hi>Wrangel,</hi> Count <hi>Podelctoski</hi> the Princes favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:150241:91"/>accompanied with the Baron, and followed by fifty Hey-Dukes of his Guard, went out to meet him. After the Compliments his Eyes were bound over with a Scarf; and being introduced thro the Pond-gate, he was conducted in that manner in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lower Court of the Prince's Caſtle, where they gave him the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of his ſight. It was there that <hi>Wrangel</hi> appeared in an extreme ſurprize, to ſee ſo much magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence in a City of War. But it was much augmented when <hi>Zamoski,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by two hundred Gentlemen, and the braveſt of his Court, came and received him in his ſecond Court, and treated him with all the civility he could have expected. After the firſt Ceremonies, he led him into an apartment, whoſe furniture was ſo rich, and all the reſt ſo well ſuted, that he had never ſeen any thing more magnificent; he could not forbear looking and admiring. But
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:150241:92"/>the Prince having a mind to ſurprize him after another manner, and had ſecretly given order for the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a great ſupper, where Delicacy and Profuſion made it equally per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that he was not in a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of apprehending to want Victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als. When all was prepared, he conducted the Collonel into a great Hall, where ſeveral Tables were ſerved in the ſame Order; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cauſed him to ſit by him, while they were thus feaſting, a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cert of Muſick and Trumpets divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them ſo agreeably, that <hi>Wrangel</hi> fancied himſelf in an Enchanted Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. But after having been well entertained, the Prince who was no leſs Gallant than he was brave, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Wrangel</hi> into another Hall, where all the Ladies of the Town, and ſeveral others of the Country who had took refuge there before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eg, coming here a moment after in extraordinary dreſſes, he begun
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:150241:92"/>the Ball which inſted a good part of the night; inſomuch that the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel not being able to teſtifie his ſatisfaction to the Prince, went to bed without ſpeaking of affairs. The day after <hi>Zamoski</hi> coming to him in his Chamber, after that all the people were retired, <hi>Wrangel</hi> told him that the King his Maſter hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perticular eſteem for his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, both for his merit, and the great courage he had ſhown ſince the ſieg, he had conceived the thoughts of marrying him to a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of his blood, and that in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of this marriage, he would erect <hi>Zamoski</hi> into a Soveraignty, with a greater extent of land than then depended on it. That for this he only demanded the Right of inveſtiture in the ſame manner as the Elector of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> held <hi>Pruſſia,</hi> and that for ſurety he might during three years keep a Garriſon in the Place. And having likewiſe added
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:150241:93"/>ſeveral other Circumſtances capable to ſeduce a weak man; the Prince, who was not of this Character, and whoſe zeal and fidelity for King <hi>Caſimer</hi> had appeared in ſeveral Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, eying <hi>Wrangel,</hi> told him with a haughty air, that having done nothing that might oblige the King his Maſter to make him Propoſitions ſo prejudicial to his honour, he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to aſſure him that he would find in the ſequel of the ſieg, as much courage and reſiſtance in the leaſt of the Inhabitants of his Town, as he had found weakneſs and inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity in <hi>Caſimer</hi>'s other Subjects, and that he ſhould defend himſelf to the utmoſt extremity: and that if fortune made the King his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour, he believed him ſo gener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that he would treat him like a man of his Quality, and that he would honour him with his eſteem. After this diſcourſe having drawn up all his Troops in Battail, and ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:150241:93"/>
               <hi>Wrangel</hi> if having ſo many brave men he would counſel him to render. The Collonel who was charmed as well with tho Prince's good Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment as his generous Reſolution, after having thanked him for the honours he had received, aſſured him that he would all his life time be full of acknowledgment; and asked his permiſſion to retire: whereupon <hi>Wrangel</hi> himſelf bound his ſcarf upon his Eyes, and thoſe who had brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>im, having ieconducted him to the place where they had received him, the recital he made to the King of all we have mentioned, ſo ſurprized this Prince; that his Army being already much diminiſhed, as well by the number of the dead and wounded, as by diſeaſes and diſertions, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to raiſe the ſieg, which he did the night following, and retired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tored-<hi>Ruſſia,</hi> upon the River <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zane. Zamoski</hi> being thus gloriouſly deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, abandoned himſelf entirely
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:150241:94"/>to the cares of his Love, and having cauſed the Baron to enter into his Cloſet, it is time, ſaid he to him, with a very paſſionate Tone, that I ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit my ſelf of what I have promiſed; we have no longer any Enemies to fight with, nor a City to defend: Wherefore let us return to Court and aſſure by our preſence her for whoſe ſake life is only pleaſant to me, that I am ever faithful. If I ſtayed lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger here ſhe would have reaſon to complain, and I would rather die than give her the leaſt occaſion to do ſo. The Baron was extremely pleaſed to ſee the Prince had ſo ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſentements for <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> and was no leſs impatient than he to be there. But being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the ſame day that the ſieg was raiſed that <hi>Caſimer</hi> had quitted <hi>Oppol,</hi> and was come with all the Court to the Caſtle of <hi>Glogow,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to Count <hi>Dosbreſtol;</hi> he made the Prince comprehend that
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:150241:94"/>the Enemies having ſeveral flying Camps in the field, it was to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he might fall into their hands, and thus it would be more conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent he alone ſhould take a voyage to <hi>Glogow,</hi> ſince he would not only render an exact account of all that had paſſed in the ſieg, but that he would make likewiſe known the ſtate his paſſion had put him in, and that he would take ſuch meaſures as were requiſite for their ſeeing one another with ſafety, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Commerce of Letter. And that it might otherwiſe come to paſs that the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> coming to know that he had quitted <hi>Zamoſch,</hi> would not fail to beſieg it again, which would occaſion without doubt the loſs of the place. And therefore that he ought for all theſe reaſons let him run the riſque of a journy, which <hi>Zamoski</hi> could hardly be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to: Yet after having ſtill a long time perſiſted in his firſt Reſolution,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:150241:95"/>having at length drawn up an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for the King of the Principal Circumſtances of the ſieg, he refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the Baron the care of acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him with the reſt, and diſmiſſing him gave him this Letter for <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT was very juſt, Mademoiſelle, that after having rendred you the abſolute Miſtreſs of my heart, I ſhould likewiſe vanquiſh the King of</hi> Sweden, <hi>that I might make you a double homage of his defeat and my Own. But what glory ſoever I have procured by having ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Courſe of his Victeries, I ſhall have reaſon to complain of my fate, if you are not perſwaded that I think the paſſion I have of ſerving you, a thouſand times more glorious. Yes, Mademoiſelle, nothing is comparable to my love; and abſence which deſtroys the greateſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, has ſo augmented mine, that I die with impatience to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e you again. How happy ſhould I be if you had the
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:150241:95"/>ſame earneſtneſs! but, alas! how great is my misfortune to be forced to ſtay here; and why muſt a beaten Enemy hinder me from going to declare my ſelf entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Yours</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Zamoski.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>If the Prince was much in pain to part with the Baron, this laſt had yet much more to get to <hi>Glogow;</hi> he had a above a dozen times like to have been taken by Swediſh parties, and it was thro a Kind of miracle that he came at length to Court. <hi>Caſimer</hi> who had been informed of the ſieg of <hi>Zamoſch,</hi> and who knew not what the ſucceſs had been of it, took an extreme delight in learning from the Baron all the particulars of what had paſſed, and that the Prince had determined in favour of <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> for whom he begun to have no longer ſo much paſſion, tho he had ſtill for her a great deal of good w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll. All the
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:150241:96"/>Court took part in this good ſucceſs, as may be imagined. But after that <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> had read the Prince's Letter, and that the Baron had likewiſe acqainted her with ſeveral particulars that perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded her of his paſſion. That fair perſon had ſuch a contentment of mind as cannot be deſcribed. The Queen obſerved it with vexation, and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem</hi> as young as ſhe was, being but fourteen years old, would alſo have ſuffered it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impatiently, if her heart had been very ſenſible for the Prince. But as <hi>Sobieski,</hi> tho he was but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Crown, pleaſed her more, and ſhe in ſome manner acted more out of Complaiſance to the Queen than inclination: Her diſpleaſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Zamoski,</hi> who had neither writ to the Queen nor her, had its real ſource only from the jealouſy that Ladies uſually have the one for the other, when they are to diſpute for
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:150241:96"/>the prize of Beauty. The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs had likewiſe all manner of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to applaud the Barons conſtancy: And as he had extremely well ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in his voyage, and that they had made it a point of honour to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the marriage of the Prince with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimer</hi> whoſaw her daily in her apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, had there ſeveral Conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces upon this ſubject: But well knowing that the Queen would uſe all manner of means, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying in the Baron's abſence all that had been done at <hi>Zamoſch;</hi> it was reſolved he ſhould return with all haſte, under pretence of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prince, and of cauſing him to raiſe a Regiment: Wherefore he cauſed a Commiſſion to be expedited and delivered the nececeſſary mony to the Baron, with whom having concerted how he ſhould addreſs all the Prince's Letters and his own to the King, who gave order to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luz.</hi>
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:150241:97"/>Gentleman of his Chamber to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, he returned to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with a very kind anſwer from <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield.</hi> The King of <hi>Sweden</hi> during the Sieg of <hi>Zamoſch,</hi> ſent <hi>Duglas</hi> with Troops to beſieg <hi>Premiflie;</hi> but tho that City was not in a poſture of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining a Sieg in the formes, the Burghers were ſo apprehenſive of the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Government, that the they had but ſimple Walls, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved rather to die than to render the place. They ſhut up the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Children in the Churches, and while that theſe implored the ſuccours of Heaven, <hi>Duglas</hi> having paſſed the River over the Ice to ſeize on the gate, they repulſed him with ſo much vigour, that he loſt above two hundred men in his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacque, and the Ice breaking in his retreat he had many more drown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Inſo much that he returned with much confuſion to his Maſter
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:150241:97"/>who was extreamly ſurprized with all theſe ill ſucceſſes. <hi>Charneski</hi> having notice that he cauſed a Bridge to be made over the <hi>Zane,</hi> and that a thouſand Horſe guarded the Carpenters, he advanced with his Troops into a Wood, where he laid two Regiments in Ambuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cade. And having ſent two others Armed after the <hi>Tartarian</hi> manner, to charge the <hi>Swedes,</hi> they engaged them to fight, and by pretending to run away, having drawn them beyond the Ambuſcade, the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand <hi>Swedes</hi> were defeated, except ſome few who eſcaped, the bridge was broken and almoſt all the bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage taken by <hi>Charneski,</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired without having loſt more than thirty Troopers.</p>
            <p>The King ſeeing his Troops dayly diminiſhed by diſeaſes, by the rigour of the ſeaſon, and by all the advantages that <hi>Charneski</hi> gained, he reſolved to retreat and recover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:150241:98"/>the banck of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſtule,</hi> for the preſerving what was left him. <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neski</hi> did all he could to draw him into open field that he might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by a Battail to ſettle the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Caſimer</hi> upon a good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation; and to that purpoſe he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacqued him rather like a deſperate man than a good Captain. But <hi>Charles</hi> being no leſs cunning than himſelf, and whoſe good fortune begun to diminiſh, having pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trated his deſign, employed all his prudence to avoid him, inſomuch that he would never quit the Rivers banck, and all the <hi>Swedes</hi> who went a ſtray or could not follow, were cut in pieces without quarter. As the moſt part of the great Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad engaged themſelves with <hi>Charles</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ragieskies</hi> ſollicitation, and the others without making reflexion that they delivered themſelves up to their greateſt Enemy, the good ſucceſſes of <hi>Charncski</hi> made them
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:150241:98"/>juſtly afraid of being one day pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed for it. This made them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to returne timely to their devoir. <hi>Lubomierski Mareſchal</hi> of the Kingdom, <hi>Calinski, Broſcoski, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander Conieſpolski, Nicolas Potoski,</hi> and <hi>Sapieska</hi> quitted <hi>Charles</hi> Party, and joyned themſelves with their Troops to the brave <hi>Charneski.</hi> Only <hi>George Niemiviez</hi> with ſome of his continued in his Rebellion. It is eaſy to conceive the extream per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity that <hi>Charles</hi> was in after this deſertion. He diſſembled his vexation as well as he could, and ſeeing that it was very dangerous to ſtay any longer in the field, he retired to the Caſtle of <hi>Rudnie,</hi> where <hi>Charneski</hi> having joyned him, there was a very ſharp fight. More than two thoſand <hi>Swedes</hi> loſt their lives, and if the ſuccours <hi>Charneski</hi> expected had arrived, the King of <hi>Sweden</hi> had been entirely defeated. He was obliged to make a haſty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat,
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:150241:99"/>not being able to reach <hi>Sando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> where he had a good Garriſon. <hi>Charneski</hi> followed him with the ſame diligence, he fought him the third time, and it was with incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable dangers that <hi>Charles</hi> got to <hi>Warſaw,</hi> accompained by few of his men, and was perſued as far as the Suburbe. There run a report that he was killed, and all <hi>Europe</hi> ſo poſitively believed it during ſome Months, that it was a kind of crime to doubt it. The Queen his Wife was as much allarum'd as others and ſhe paſſed the Sea to learn the certain News of it; and it was of that advantage to <hi>Caſimer,</hi> that his affairs thereupon entirely changed face. General <hi>Steembock</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Mariemburg,</hi> which had been admirably well defended for ſix Weeks that the Siege had been formed. Baron <hi>Spar,</hi> Originally a <hi>Swede,</hi> and whoſe Father had dwelt in <hi>Poland</hi> from the time of
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:150241:99"/>
               <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> was Commander of it, with <hi>James Veyer</hi> and his Brother, they did certainly all that could be expected both from their Conduct and Generoſity. But the Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition beginning to fail in the place, and the three thouſand men that were ſent from <hi>Dantzick</hi> to ſuccour it, being deceived by the <hi>Swedes,</hi> who under pretext of deſerting made them believe the City was taken, which obliged them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire without expecting further News. <hi>Spar</hi> ſeeing he could not hold out any longer, rendred upon an Honorable Compoſition. This loſs tho conſiderable was in ſome manner repaired the ſame day. For the Marqueſs of <hi>Baden</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed of the extremity <hi>Charles</hi> was in, came to his ſuccours with freſh Troops, but was fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by <hi>Charneski,</hi> who immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately defeated three Troops of Horſe. The Marqueſs not being
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:150241:100"/>in a Condition to fight him, paſſed the River <hi>de Pilſee</hi> over a Bridge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning to get to <hi>Warſaw.</hi> But <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neski</hi> being deſirous to engage him, and to take the advantage of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, ſwam over the River with his men. <hi>Baden</hi> not being able any longer to avoid it, prepared for ſight and hid part of his Cavallery in the Woods. The Battail laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed above two hours, and ſeveral were killed on both ſides. But in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine <hi>Baden</hi> fled, and <hi>Charneski</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued him as far as <hi>Warſaw,</hi> tho a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſeaven leagues thither. The <hi>Swedes</hi> were almoſt all cut in pieces, their Canon their bagage and moſt part of their Colours were took by the <hi>Polanders.</hi> All theſe happy ſucceſſes made <hi>Charles</hi> know that fortune is not alwaies conſtant. <hi>Charneski</hi> recovered with the ſame vigour <hi>Lovitz,</hi> an <hi>Archiepiſcopal</hi> See, where the <hi>Swedes</hi> had much booty. And General <hi>Iſrael</hi> having endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:150241:100"/>to oppoſe him, he was no more ſucceſſful than the Marqueſs, inſomuch that <hi>Charneski</hi> being advanced into <hi>Domerella,</hi> he took in ſeveral ſmall Cities, and ſent three Senators to <hi>Dantzick</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Magiſtrates with theſe good ſucceſſes, and the ſuccours that <hi>Caſimer</hi> was preparing. The Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> was coming to <hi>Pruſſia.</hi> The <hi>Danzickers</hi> fitted out ſeveral Veſſels to trie to take her, but could not do it. She landed at the <hi>Pillaw,</hi> where the Electour of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> received her with Honours and Teſtimonies of very great joy. The King her Husband having ſomething refreſhed himſelf at <hi>Warſaw,</hi> and given the remnants of his Army to <hi>Wittemburg,</hi> he went to meet her with <hi>Baden, Sulsback</hi> and <hi>Radzivil,</hi> he paſſed by <hi>Elbing,</hi> and being arrived at the <hi>Pillaw,</hi> his preſence, his tenderneſs and all his Careſſes made the Queen forget the
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:150241:101"/>Pains ſhe had ſuffered. After having ſtayed there ſome time, they return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Elbing</hi> with greater deſigns than ever of continuing the War.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> to this effect writ to all the <hi>Palatines</hi> and Poliſh Lords, who had quitted his Party, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their duty, calling them Rebels, and proteſting that if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twenty days they acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not their fault, he would never pardon them. And being deſirous to repare with his pen what he had loſt by his Sword, he writ likewiſe to the Magiſtrates of <hi>Dantzick,</hi> and complained that they would have ſuccoured <hi>Mariembourg,</hi> and ſurprize the Queen, tho he and his Predeceſſors had done them ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, favours, that however being willing to uſe Clemency, if they returned to their duty, he would receive them upon favourable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, if not they were to expect all the rigour that War permits. But
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:150241:101"/>that Letter made not any impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion upon their minds, and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates anſwered him in few words, that having preſerved for two hundred years an inviolable fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to the Kings of <hi>Poland,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was capable of making them abandon King <hi>Caſimer,</hi> upon whom he made War without any reaſon; That if after having defended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves like men of honour, the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of War ſhould bring them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Power, they hoped he would treat them better than the other Cities that had not done their Duty. Tho this anſwer was not conform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to <hi>Charles</hi>'s ſentiments, he could not forbear commending their fidelity; and not being in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to reduce them by force, he leſt <hi>Steemooth</hi> before the pſace, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the Succours that was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him from <hi>Germany,</hi> having joyned <hi>Wrangel</hi> near unto a wood, he was informed that <hi>Charneski</hi> was on
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:150241:102"/>the other ſide with his Troops, he gave order to the Colonel to attacque him, which he did: the Shoque was terrible, and coſt ſeveral lives. But <hi>Charneski</hi> ſeeing the King approach at the head of the reſt of the Army, he retreated in good order with the advantage he had won. The Night favoured his Deſign, and the King being advanced as far as <hi>Torne,</hi> learnt there the extremity his Garriſon was reduced to at <hi>Warſaw. Caſimer</hi> who was preparing at <hi>Glogow</hi> to return into his Kingdom with the ſuccours of the Tartars which he expected, learnt likewiſe there the happy ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of <hi>Charneski,</hi> with all the joy imaginable; and the Baron <hi>de Saint-C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> who was arrived at <hi>Zamoſch</hi> without any danger, having alſo let him know that the Prince hoped in a little time to joyn him at the head of two thouſand horſe, and that he perſevered in the deſign of marrying <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> for whom
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:150241:102"/>his paſſion was ſtill the ſame, one may ſay that from the time <hi>Caſimer</hi> had quitted his Realm, his mind had never been more agreeably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. But the Queen whoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mireable penetration made her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the moſt ſecret intrigues, and who was not eaſily changed, was not long without knowing the true Occaſion of the Baron's ſtay with the Prince; great ſucceſſes as well as great troubles cannot be well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> was too well pleaſed, not to let ſomething of it be known, and did not fail to impart it to one of her Companions, whom ſhe believed her friend; and the Queen likewiſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving her more ſtrictly than uſual, knew at length all that paſſed. Her promiſes and civilities having not had that effect upon the Prince ſhe had expected, ſhe changed her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. Count <hi>Podelotoski</hi> was the Prince's Favourite, and abſolutely
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:150241:103"/>governed him, wherefore ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him to ſerve her as well by her preſents as by his own intereſt. For having made him comprehend that if the Prince married <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> whoſe wit he was acquainted withall, ſhe would not fail to deſtroy his favour, and ruine his fortune, for that ſhe would particularly informe her ſelf of all things; whereas <hi>Mademoiſelle d' Arquiem</hi> being a young perſon of fourteen years old, without any experience of the affairs of the world, if the Prince married her, this Marriage would not only be much more advantageous to him, but he might alſo continue in the favour his merit had procured him, to which ſhe would contribute on her part, and even augment it if it was poſſible. And adding to all theſe conſiderations great hopes, and that the King was in love with <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> which
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:150241:103"/>obliged him to wiſh ſhe was Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Prince. There need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no more for the determining the Count to oppoſe the Baron. In effect from the time the Queen had opened her ſelf to him in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, he fought all poſſible occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to traverſe his deſigns. And as he had acquired a great familiarity with the Prince, whoſe affairs he abſolutely governed with the ſame Authority he did his own; Being one day informed that <hi>Zamoski</hi> and the Baron were together in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, he went thither in all haſt with a reſolution of interrupting their diſcourſe, and to begin by ſomething that ſhould make a noiſe to make his Court to the Queen: But the Arbour door being ſhut, he knocked ſo hard that the Prince was angry, and notwithſtanding all the kindneſs he had for this indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet Courtier, had like to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded him as briskly as he had
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:150241:104"/>ſhown little reſpect. Yet being a man of wit, and perceiving an al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in his Maſters face; he told him he was to ſpeak to him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout an important affair, and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing inſenſibly led hem into a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Alley far enough from the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, where they had left the Baron, he preſented him with an open Letter and prayed him to read it, which he did. But taking notice, that it was addreſſed to the Baron, and that it had been opened, he took it ill, and with ſome heat let him know his ſurprize. Inſomuch that he told the Prince that a Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier of the Garriſon had delivered him that Letter, which had been given him by an unknown perſon, who had retired himſelf, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving that mention was made therein of him, he thought his duty ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged him to bring it him in all haſt to diſpoſe of it as he ſhould think fit. You had done much better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:150241:104"/>the Prince very ſharply, to have given it to him to whom it is addreſſed to, and not to meddle with an others ſecrets, and not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Count time to reply, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to the Arbour, where he acquainted the Baron with what had paſſed in the Alley. As this Letter was from <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield,</hi> and that ſhe therein gave notice to the Baron that the Queen had diſcovered their ſecret, that he ought to ſuſpect the Count, and in fine that ſhe apprehended the Prince would abandon her to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf wholly to <hi>Mademoiſelle d' Arquiem.</hi> After having read it over together, and looked upon one another for ſome time without ſpeaking a word; at length the Prince ſighing, interrupted their ſilence, and held this diſcourſe to the Baron: Am not I much to be pitied to love with ſo much tenderneſs and ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as I do, and yet to be ſuſpected
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:150241:105"/>of inconſtancy, after having given ſo many teſtimonies of my fidelity; and are not we very unhappy, in that our ſecret is diſcovered, and that to ſurprize me, the Queen has engaged the Count to travers what makes all my joy? What you have ſaid, my Lord, (replied the Baron) is ſo reaſonable, that I can only ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud your having ſo generous ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But if I durſt tell you my thoughts, <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanfield</hi> is not to be blaimed for being in fear of being abandoned, ſince it is an infallible mark of the eſteem ſhe has for you, the Queen is againſt her, ſhe makes you very advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous offers: <hi>Mademo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſelle de Arquiem</hi> is young and pretty, and has the honour to belong to her; and the Count promiſes to make you change the good ſentiments you have for her; all this joyned together makes her with juſtice be allarm'd: But my Lord, that you may not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:150241:105"/>her of being ſo too ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly, you muſt know that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs ſends me word, that the Queen has promiſed the Count a Staroftie of a thouſand pound yearly income, for to oblige you to think no more of her; and having ſpoke theſe words ſhe ſhewed the Prince the Letter; this news made ſuch an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon his mind, that after having been in a great paſſion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Count, he reſolved not to give credit to any thing he ſhould tell him; and if he had not had the care of the affairs of his Family, he would without doubt have diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. He lived for ſome days with him after a more reſerved man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and purpoſely avoided all the occaſions of being alone that he might not diſcourſe him. But it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing impoſſible to live long in that conſtraint, becauſe he was to render him an account of his affairs, this cunning Favourite did not complain
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:150241:106"/>of the Prince's indifference, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſome manner reeſtabliſhed in his former liberty, in the end he fancied he might ſucceed in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign. The hopes of a Staroſty, and the honour of being the Queens Confident ſo ſenſibly touched him, that he could not forbear intermix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with his affairs ſomething of the Prince's Amours, for the endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to oblige him to explain himſelf to him: However he did it not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would keep them ſecret till all was regulated for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding his marriage. This reſerved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs augmented his curioſity, and the Queen preſſing him to make known to her the ſtate of affairs, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to do his utmoſt for the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying her. The Prince loved hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very much, and as it was his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Recreation, the Count fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied it might furniſh him with a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable Occaſion to diſcourſe him. In the Woods that are near <hi>Zamoſch,</hi>
               <pb n="201" facs="tcp:150241:106"/>there are ſeen numbers of Bears, Wild-Boors, and other Beaſts of that kind, he ordered the Count to prepare the neceſſary things for this Divertiſement: Wherefore he aſſembled two or three thouſand Peaſants; and having cauſed the Woods to be ſurrounded with Nets, as is uſually practized in that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, while the Peaſants beat the Woods, and the Dogs purſued the Beaſts, the Count being alone near the Prince in a place the thing ought neceſſarily to paſs thro, ſeeing him attentive and penſive, I allways fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied till now, my Lord, ſaid he to him, that my ſervices were pleaſing to you, and I flattered my ſelf to have ſo well correſponded to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour you have done me in truſting me with the affairs of moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, that I believed my fidelity being known to you, you would not conceal from me the ſentiments of your heart. But if it was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:150241:107"/>me to complain of my ill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune rather than of any thing elſe, have I not reaſon to believe, that you have no longer the ſame kindneſs for me that you have been pleaſed to honour me with; ſince that you have not only been very reſerved of late in the diſcourſes that neceſſity ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liges me to have with you, and you do not even give me all the time I have occaſion for. But if I durſt ſay it, my Lord, I am the laſt of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom who knows not that you are going to marry <hi>Mademoiſelle de Schanſield.</hi> And you have made to me a miſtery of the moſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant thing of your Life, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I might have given you a great and moſt ſenſible mark of my fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Yet in ſtead of murmuring, Heaven is my Witn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſs that I would never have ſpoke to you of it, if my honour had not forced me rather to incurr your diſpleaſure than to fail telling you, that it is not for
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:150241:107"/>your advantage, and that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours are uſed to ſurprize you in flattering agreeably the paſſion you have for her, Yes, my Lord, you are plaid upon, and I have advice from ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good hands that the King has a long time loved her, and that he is again beloved. Inſomuch that the Queen being jealous, the Baron <hi>de Saint-Cir</hi> only ſtays with you for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to oblige you to marry her: But, my Lord, if you are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to marry, you will find matches at Court, much more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and becoming you both by their Birth and Fortune. The Princes of your Family have ever made illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Alliances, you ought to follow their Examples for the maintaining your Rank, and if I durſt give you Counſels, it would be much more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to think of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Arquiem;</hi> ſhe is younger and more beautiful, and will better comply with your humour, and has likewiſe the
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:150241:108"/>honour to belong to the Queen. In fine you poſſeſs her heart without fearing that any other has reigned there before you, and this reaſon alone ſhould oblige you to prefer her, ſince you will only have the Perſon and not the heart of <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Schanfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The end of the firſt Part.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150241:108"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
